<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remember Lots wife Two godly and fruitfull sermons verie conuenient for this our time: lately preached on a Sunday in the Cathedral Church of S. Peters, in Excester: the one, in the forenoone: the other, in the afternoone the same day. By Iohn C.</title>
            <author>Carpenter, John, d. 1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852056</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 311:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remember Lots wife Two godly and fruitfull sermons verie conuenient for this our time: lately preached on a Sunday in the Cathedral Church of S. Peters, in Excester: the one, in the forenoone: the other, in the afternoone the same day. By Iohn C.</title>
                  <author>Carpenter, John, d. 1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[124] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin, and are to be solde by Edward White at the litle North-doore of S. Paules, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Carpenter.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Two godly sermons.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17358:1"/>
            <p>¶ Remember <hi>Lots wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two godly and fruitfull</hi> Sermons verie conuenient <hi>for this our time: lately preached</hi> on a Sunday in the Cathedral Church of S. Peters in Exceſter: the one, in the forenoone: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the afternoone the ſame day.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24.</bibl>
               <p>He that endureth to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Thomas Orwin, <hi>and are to be ſolde by</hi> Edward White at the litle North-doore of S. Paules, at the ſigne of the Gunne. 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17358:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17358:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipfull and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Matrone, Miſtris <hi>Mary Woolton,</hi> wife to the Right Reuerend Father in Chriſt, <hi>Iohn,</hi> Lord Biſhop of Exceſter, Grace, faith and felicitie in the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (Right worſhipful) that worldly wittes doe deſire to heare rather <hi>Eliphas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad</hi> and <hi>Zophar,</hi> the <hi>Themanite,</hi> the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hite</hi> and the <hi>Naamathite,</hi> to paynt forth a bad matter eloquently: than patient <hi>Iob,</hi> to handle a very good cauſe with playnneſſe and ſimplicitie. To whoſe curious heads and itching eares, mine harriſh harmonie deuoyd of learned method, vtterance &amp; grace, may ſeeme
<pb facs="tcp:17358:3"/> altogether vnpleaſant. Howbeit, I am not, for all that, all vnwilling (vpon iuſt occaſions) now to publiſh that, which before I neuer ment to make publicke, otherwiſe then by worde only. For I perſwade my ſelfe of the goodneſſe of my cauſe, and aduenture to promiſe it, both profitable and godly. Beſides that, the candle once lightened is not for the Buſhell, but for the Table: the talent ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand, is not to be hidden, but to be employed. And the light that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man hath in him, muſt ſo ſhine on euery part, as thereby the name of God may be glorified, and the godly edified. Neither ought a Chriſtian to bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of Chriſt and of his word, ſeeme it vnto worldlings neuer ſo contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Finally, to commit that thing to perpetuitie, which is for the benefite of the brethren any way, is as commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as it is profitable, and oftentimes commaunded to bee done in the word of God, as an eſpeciall helpe for mans
<pb facs="tcp:17358:3"/> minde, which (being as water that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly loſeth any impreſsion) without ſuch memorandums, doth very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forget things memorable and moſt neceſſary. Therefore the Lord doth not only write his commandements in two tables of ſtone: but alſo commaundeth <hi>Moſes,</hi> and after him the Prophets, and laſtly his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Iohn,</hi> to write the things which they had ſeene, and heard, being (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth) profitable for the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and (as <hi>Paule</hi> confirmeth) for our learning, that we which be the Lords, may therby be the ſooner furniſhed and prepared to euery vertue. Theſe things conſidered, might ſufficiently haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the penning of theſe two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, touching that notable memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, which our Sauiour gaue to the Iewes, <hi>Remember Lots wife:</hi> yet calling to minde with what a diligent eare and attentiuenes your ſelfe liſtened to the matter vttered (by your owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) with the good liking and ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:17358:4"/> commendations, wherewith ye beautified the ſame at that time, (beſides ſome deſires of others, thereunto, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the argument and matter right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for this time) it prouok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d me to reſume my pen with the more dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; readines, to gather vp (as it were,) into a ſtore baſket the fragme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of that ſpirituall banquet, which were ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red abroad, as iuſtly as I could, to bee and remayne to and for the vſe of them that had before taſted of the ſame: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that they which liked it before, will not loath it now: &amp; nothing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by the grace of God, but that it will be to his glorie and the benefite of his Church, the only marke which I haue aymed vnto. In reſpect whereof wee may not ſticke (if wee bee the Lords) to hazard all the credit that wee haue, yea and rather wiſh with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> to be as <hi>Anathema</hi> among them of this world, then that we ſhould hold backe, or thruſt to obliuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing that maie
<pb facs="tcp:17358:4"/> be to the aduauncement of the one, or profite of the other. Hauing therefore preſerued by pen, &amp; noted theſe words in a Booke, I both commit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to the Church of Chriſt, and among the true members of the ſame, eſpecially to your Worſhip, by whoſe often courteſies to me, I am mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to thankfulnes, and by whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie choyce of good <hi>Mary</hi> her lot, I am ſtirred vp to gladneſſe: the token &amp; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification whereof my good-will vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto you in this my preſent, which (though ſo ſimple in ſhewe) is for the matter as pretious as pure gold tryed in the fire. Therefore I pray you to accept it gladly, to reade it at your conuenient leiſure, and repoſe the profite thereof in your breaſt, that therby ye may both be comforted your ſelf with <hi>Mary:</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may the rather (as otherwiſe ye are well able) (God be thanked) perſwade others, not only women, but alſo men, to follow Chriſt in faithfull zeale, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17358:5"/> and vertue, without wearines or fainting. The Lord God graunt, that the hearers and readers of this Booke, may not only thereby the ſooner tend to the right vſe of memorie therein taught them: but alſo learne to go foorth from <hi>Sodom,</hi> to proceed, and to hold on with iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> towards the goale of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life: &amp; on the other ſide, with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to eſchew the horrible ſinnes and faults of <hi>Lots</hi> wife, by the conſideration of the fearefull iudgements of God on that vnhappie woman. And euen thus, I commend both my good Lord and your ſelfe to the Almightie Lord, who bleſſe, preſerue and keepe you vnder the wings of his mightie prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>the 28. day of Iune. 1588.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips to my power in Chriſt.</hi> Iohn Carpenter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17358:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>O Lord open thou my lippes, and my mouth ſhall ſhew foorth thy prayſe. Open the cares of thy people, that they may heare: and encline all our hearts to beleeue and followe thoſe things that be taught vs in thy holie Word, through Ieſus Chriſt thy deere Sonne our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  <bibl>Luke. 17. Verſe. 32.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>Remember Lots Wife.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Lord God be ſo holie, and glorious,<note place="margin">Ezech. 1.</note> that no man can behold him, and the verie Angels be vnable to ſuſteine the brightnes of his face: And on the other ſide, man is ſo vncleane, and ignominious,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.19. Geneſ. 6.</note> ſo ſtiffe-necked, and ſtubborne hearted, ſo wicked, and abhominable, that he is forced with the Publican to hang downe his head in great confuſion: with <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dani. 9.4. Pſal. 8.4. Hebr. 2.6.</note> to graunt the due deſert of open ſhame: with <hi>Dauid,</hi> to admire that euer God would vouchſafe either to regard or remember man: and that
<pb facs="tcp:17358:6"/> all men from the higheſt of them to the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, can not but confeſſe with bluſhing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that all men be not onely conceiued and borne in ſinne, but alſo bred and brought vp in the ſame, being méere lyers, and lighter than vanitie.<note place="margin">Pſal. 116. verſe. 11. Dan 9.11 Ezech. 18. verſe. 21. Pſal. 51.9.</note> Yet becauſe that to the Lord belongeth mercie and forgiuenes, he turneth away his face from mans ſinnes, being euer mindfull of mercies. He foretelleth men of his iudgements prouoked, and giueth them timely warning to eſchewe the plagues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, with a ſweete prouocation of ſinnes to fruitfull repentance, either by comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table arguments of his bounties to his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children,<note place="margin">Sap. 10.</note> or by ſtrange and fearefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of his iudgements executed on the rebellious and vngodly ſinners. In like manner, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that true <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and friend to mankinde, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating in this (as in all other things) his heauenly Father, who of his loue to man, according to the purport and effect of the auntient promiſe made to <hi>Adam,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to <hi>Abraham, Dauid,</hi> and other god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers in his mercy, ſent him into the world to bring all true beleeuers vnto life euerlaſting, doth not only by perfitting the worke of mans ſaluation, which none could
<pb facs="tcp:17358:6"/> do but himſelfe, ſhewe great mercies vnto his beloued: but alſo foreſheweth both to them, and all others, a moſt miſerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction imminent and ready to fall, firſt on the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and then, on all others, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their ſtubbornes, faithleſſe ingratitude, and Apoſtaſie, do deſpiſe the goodnes of God: and he leaueth not vnwarned in the ſame all men, to take heed of thoſe future miſeries that horrible ſinners do purchaſe to themſelues, by producing this notable <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandum</hi> of the terrible iudgements of God euen on the wife of that righteous man <hi>Lot,</hi> ſhe going about to ſaue her life, loſt it, and looking backe in her heart to ſinfull <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> from whence, the Lord in mercy had drawne her with charge to proceede with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out retire,<note place="margin">God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheweth his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> ſhe periſhed from the right way betweene <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Zoar,</hi> in that great wrath kindled againſt her.</p>
            <p>We reade in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that when all fleſh had corrupted his way on the earth,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.23</note> and the Lord ſawe that the wickednes of man was great on the earth, and all the imaginations and thoughts of his heart were only euill, in ſo much that he repented him of mans creation, and was grieued in his mind: he would yet in mercie, though in the middeſt
<pb facs="tcp:17358:7"/> of wrath, both foreſhew the deſtruction fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, vnto his righteous ſeruant <hi>Noah</hi> whome he fauoured, and gaue him alſo commiſſion to diuulgate and publiſh the ſame to the world, whome, notwithſtanding this vnreaſonable ſorrow conceiued, he would in mercie ſpare for the ſpace of an hundred and twenty yeares. And moreouer, for a perpetuall inſtruction to the poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Lord (after that <hi>Noah</hi> had obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reſt) made his Bowe in the Clowdes to be a token of the couenant thereon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted, which alſo beareth manifeſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both of mercy and iudgement: to the comfort of the godly, for whoſe benefit the promiſe was giuen: to the confuſion of the wicked, for whome deſtruction waiteth. And there is the blew colour of water, to note for euer, wherewith the world was deſtroyed: and the red colour of fire, to ſhew wherewith it ſhall periſh,<note place="margin">2. Peter. 3.</note> according to the Propheſie of <hi>S. Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 18.</note>Afterward, when the ſinnes and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the filthy <hi>Sodomites</hi> had aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp, and the loathſome cries of theſe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Sinners had pearced the Lords eares, he determined thereon a mightie Plague, which yet he threw not vpon them,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:7"/> till time he had both warned them thereof, and deliuered from the ſame his Seruants <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Booke of the <hi>Iudges</hi> it is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the Iſraelites oftentimes ſinned againſt the Lord, and incurred the plague of their tranſgreſſions: whereof likewiſe they were forewarned and admoniſhed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware by <hi>Moſes, Ioſuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut 28. verſe. 31. Ioſh. 24.</note> and other the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God. And beſides that, ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and miſeries as enſued intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ingratitude to their poſterities, were told of by the holie Prophets, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on whome the inconueniences fell had yet certaine ſignes and tokens left to be as continuall remembrances vnto them.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> ſayd to King <hi>Saul,</hi> whiles he was yet King ouer Iſrael,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 11 verſe. 23.</note> and without feare of diſgrace: <hi>The Lord hath caſt thee off from being King ouer Iſrael.</hi> And this thing (ſayd he) was alſo ſignified by the renting of his garment.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Prophet <hi>Ahia</hi> the Silonite, told <hi>Ieroboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kin. 11. verſe. 31.</note> that the Lord had rent the Kingdome of Iſrael into <hi>12.</hi> parts, and this did he prognoſticate, by renting a newe Mantell into twelue péeces.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> foreſhewing a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb facs="tcp:17358:8"/> to come, proclaimeth thus in the Lords name:<note place="margin">Iere. 35.5.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, I haue ſet pots of Wyne before the houſehold of the <hi>Reka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> but they would not drinke, obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein their fathers commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but as for you, ye haue not hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto me, as they hearkened vnto their father: therefore I will bring vpon <hi>Iuda,</hi> and vpon euery inhabiter of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> all the trouble that I haue deuiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</hi> And this was certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in his due time, when as the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> for their ſinnes were caried away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue into <hi>Babylon,</hi> their Citie being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, their Temple polluted, and all their glorie ſhadowed.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paule</hi> hauing declared both the mercie and wrath of God: mercie, in bringing the auntient <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> wrath, in ouerthrowing the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people in the wildernes, and turning <hi>(per apostrophen)</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to whome he committeth this example, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them thus: <hi>Wherefore, let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heede that he fall not.</hi> And thus did <hi>S. Peter, Iude, Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> admoniſh them to whome they wrote. Aboue all, our Sauiour Chriſt, willing to ſtirre vp not onely the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17358:8"/> but all men which reſt in careleſſe ſecuritie,<note place="margin">Chriſt foreſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Iewes.</note> and begin to bend backward, foreſéeing their ruine and miſerable thraldome, doth not only languiſh and powre foorth teares for the ſame, thereby mouing vs (if poſſible,) to wéepe for our ſelues: but alſo propheſieth deſtructions, and many heauie lots to fall on men in the world. And to the ende they may the better be admoniſhed (ſéeing the conſideration of other mens hurts may moue them to take héede) he bringeth foorth the examples of the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> of thoſe on whome the Towre in <hi>Silo</hi> fell, and of them whome <hi>Pilate</hi> ſlewe in the time of their Sacrifices, of them that were drowned in the generall Floud, and of the <hi>Sodomites.</hi> And therevnto he addeth ſemblable Parables: as of the Rich man, and poore <hi>Lazarus:</hi> of the vniuſt Steward, and the wicked Mammon: of the fiue fooliſh Virgins: of the diſobedient child: the wicked huſbandmen: the ingratefull gueſts, and ſuch like. Héere he ſetteth foorth vnto them the fearefull iudgements of God on <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, willing them by her example to take heede of deſtruction, not to looke backe from the plough, but to hold on for feare of a greeuous and horrible deſtruction. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:17358:9"/> ſayth he: <hi>Remember Lots Wife.</hi> A ſentence very briefe, yet a leſſon not for idle Scholers: fewe words, yet not for dull hearers: but as enough for a Sermon, ſo a meete <hi>memorandum</hi> for a man, during his life. The Oracles and graue ſayings of the wiſe men of yore, were very pithie, though briefe, as was that, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Know thy ſelf:</hi> and that, <hi>
                  <hi>Memento mori:</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber death.</hi> Many like ſentences wée haue in the diuine Scriptures. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt preached, <hi>Repent, Repent.</hi> So counſailed <hi>Peter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Repent, and be baptized. Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> concluſion is,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Feare God, and keep his commandements.</hi> So our Sauiour Chriſt in his preachings hath theſe ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Watch and pray: Aske, ſeeke, giue, forgiue, iudge not, condemne not, haue faith in God: Remember Lots Wife, He that goeth to the plough, and looketh backward, is not meete for the kingdom of God. O ye Iewes, remember this, leaſt vnawares yee haue your lot with Lots Wife: Oh remember this, ye that forget God, leaſt he take you away, and there be none to reſcue.</hi> An excellent perſuaſion, to haue moued the <hi>Iewes</hi> to beware of their future miſeries, and a ſemblable inſtigation
<pb facs="tcp:17358:9"/> of all men to the due conſideration of the time of viſitation, and the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to their peace. A leſſon both particular for euery Chriſtian, and alſo generall for all perſons, people, kindreds and toongs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, to learne them faithfull perſeuerance: and the ſentence may well be diuided into two parts, namely:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Action commaunded, which is,<note place="margin">Two partes.</note> 
                     <hi>Remember.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The matter or ſubiect, which is, <hi>Lots Wife.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By the former part, we be drawne to the right vſe of memorie. By the latter part, we be put in mind of two notable examples, the one, of <hi>Lot</hi> himſelfe, the other, of his Wife, in which two, there is found an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Antitheſis, both in life and lot. Héere is one example moſt comfortable, another example moſt fearefull, the one of mercie, the other of wrath: one profitable againſt deſpaire, another neceſſarie againſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: the conſideration of both which muſt ioyne in a true Chriſtian, to withſtand thoſe two fiery darts of Satan. The Lord God graunt, that we, beholding Gods mercies towards his choſen, may with faith and thankefull hearts, timely and fruitfully
<pb facs="tcp:17358:10"/> embrace the ſame: and ſéeing his terrible iudgements on the wicked world, now alſo threatned and readie to fall downe vpon the people of this age for the like, may haſtely flye and eſchue them, by ſeruing the Lord in trembling and feare, for he is a conſuming fire.</p>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>The firſt part. <hi>Remember.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Lord God, which is the true <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſearcher and knower of mans heart, perceiuing the minde of man (as now polluted with many ſinnes) to be either as hard to conceiue that which is good, as the Adamant ſtone is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: or as vnable to reteine in memorie that which ought to be euer remembre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as the ſoft waxe is to holde faſt the image therein enſealed againſt the heate of the fire, and therein alſo not vnlike to the ayre that claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth againe after diſcloſing; doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times crie out vnto man by his Prophets, by his precepts, by his works, by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and wonderfull iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Remember,</hi> and vſeth all the wayes and meanes conuenient to perſwade and drawe man to the right vſe of his memory,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:10"/> and that ſo much the more, by how much nature fayleth in accompliſhing this thing, and a diuine action ſupernaturall, (as it were, extreame to mans corrupt nature,) is required: for as the Stone by nature is <hi>deorſum tendens,</hi> deſcending to the centre, and the water which is not bound in, fléeteth abroade: ſo is mortall mans mind, prone alwayes to that which euill is, and neuer apt to goodnes, but by conſtraint; it ſoone forgetteth that which ought to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and buſieth it ſelfe ſemblablie in that, which ſhould be forgotten: and it is true indéede, that the heart of man is a vile thing and vnſearchable. Neither may we thinke, but that as in other things, ſo alſo in this, there is found a great abuſe, which we muſt endeuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to take away, before the vſe can be effectuall, that is,<note place="margin">The abuſe of our memorie.</note> by forgetting and putting out of mind the things that we learned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, and which ought not to be reteined in mind. This forgetfulnes is a preparatiue to a good remembrance:<note place="margin">A neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes.</note> for as cléere liquor may not be kept in a veſſell, before that the corrupt be powred out, and there muſt be a cleanſing of the field, before it be ſowne; ſo before mans mind can be made apt to that which is good, it muſt be cleanſed from
<pb facs="tcp:17358:11"/> that which is euill. Therefore being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to Remember, let vs make way therevnto by a good forgetfulnes. Séeing wiſedome cannot enter into a wicked heart,<note place="margin">Sap. 1.3.4. Eccleſ. 11. verſe. 10.</note> and wicked thoughts ſeparate from God, let vs take away griefe out of our hearts, and cauſe euill to depart from our fleſh, and remember our Creator in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of youth. This is the wiſemans rule: firſt, to forget, then, to remember: to remoue away euill, then to plant and mainteine the good.</p>
               <p>The Lord himſelfe is oftentimes forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (as the Scriptures teſtifie) of the ſinnes and offences of penitent ſinners, and he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all their wickednes out of his holie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that ſo he may remember them in goodnes, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> prayed him to do for himſelfe.<note place="margin">Nehe. 13. verſe. 31.</note> And héerein would our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt haue vs to be like vnto our heauenly Father, not to kéepe the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of iniuries done againſt vs by our brethren, but willingly to forget and forgiue them, as neuer minding to reuenge them: héerein,<note place="margin">Math. 5. A wicked memorie. <hi>Themisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</note> ſhall we declare our ſelues to be the children of our heauenly Father, as moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently he preacheth on the Mount. From this point do worldly men farre differ, when as they can with <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> not onely
<pb facs="tcp:17358:11"/> reteine in mind an iniurie, but ſéeke (for their profit) an vnhoneſt reuenge. But this man was cenſured to be too ſharpe of memorie, which alſo himſelfe confeſſed, whoſe words <hi>Cicero</hi> reporteth: <hi>
                     <hi>Memini quae nolo, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſci non poſſum, quae volo:</hi> That which I would not, do I remember, neither can I put out of my mind, that which I would forget.</hi> Of ſuch an vngratious memorie was <hi>Iuno</hi> noted in <hi>Vergil,</hi> who reteining the diſpleaſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued againſt the Troian Knight, did neuer giue ouer vexing and troubling him both by Sea and by land, till time ſhe was reuenged, which was noted a matter worthy great reproch in ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, and therefore he expoſtulateth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tantae ne animis coelestibus irae?</hi> that is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Should heauenly hearts harbour ſuch hatreds?</hi> And another pointeth at the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of ſuch, <hi>Qui vir ſiem, &amp;c. <hi>He ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowe my might, what I am, and what I can do, when I haue drawne out of his bloud.</hi>
                  </hi> This kind of memorie is too much vſed among men, which they haue brought into an Arte, vnſkilfull in the meane time of the right Art of Memorie in déede. Now loue &amp; charitie is cold: faith is ſcarce found vpon the earth, the malice of man is great,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:12"/> and miſchiefe being once conceiued, he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth to bring her foorth, neither is he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, vntill he be eaſed: whoſe wood affection and fleſhly bent,<note place="margin">Ouid. eleg. <hi>1.</hi> li. Ah tu ne dubita. &amp;c. <hi>Gen. 4.</hi>
                  </note> another decyphereth thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ah nothing but reuenge muſt eaſe my deadly wo!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this ſort curſſed <hi>Caine</hi> remembred his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> enuying the acceptation of his Sacrifice before his owne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon tooke occaſion to kill him. Thus the Sonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> challenged a cauſe of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt their brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and ſold him away. Thus <hi>Haman</hi> in the Booke of <hi>Heſter</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heſt.</note> calling to mind, what the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam.</note> had once done to <hi>Agag,</hi> and the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites</hi> (from whome he deſcended) conſpired againſt the whole ſtocke of the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> Thus <hi>Eſau</hi> remembred that his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iacob</hi> had both ſupplanted him in his birthright, and preuented him in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and therevpon reſolueth: <hi>My father will dye ſhortly, and then I will kill Iacob my brother.</hi> Thus the Lords of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the wiſe men there, enuying the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of <hi>Daniell</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> in the ſpirit of Propheſie, and his royall fauour with the King, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, and cauſed him to be throwne into the Lions denne. Thus <hi>Abſalon</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
<pb facs="tcp:17358:12"/> 
                  <hi>Ammon,</hi> and flew him vnder colour of fréendſhip. So the Scribes, the Phariſes, and the high Prieſts, remembring how the Lord had often ſpoken againſt their pride, hypocriſie, and manifold abhominations, conſpired together againſt him, and neuer left off, vntill they had nayled him to the trée. Finally,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> the auntient enemie of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, bearing in mind that malediction, which the Lord caſt on him for his perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſe againſt man, leaueth not to perſecute the Woman and her Child, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> witneſſeth in his <hi>Apocalyps.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 12.</note> It ſéemeth a marueilous wiſedome to the men of this world, to imitate him therein: but they ſhall finde (as <hi>S. Iames</hi> teacheth) that this wiſedome is not of God:<note place="margin">Iam. 3.15.16.17.</note> for the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of mercie and good fruites, without iudging, without ſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As for this wiſedome of theirs, the ſame Apoſtle calleth it earthly, ſenſuall, and diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: for where enuying and ſtrife is, there is ſedition, and all euill works. The craft and drift of the Deuill is, to ſet men by the eares, that they may worſhip him in ſuch déedes of darkenes,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> whiles he laugheth at their madnes and folly. <hi>Sic malus exultat
<pb facs="tcp:17358:13"/> daemon, &amp;c.</hi> And ſéeing againe, that by the bloud of the Lamb he is ouercome, and his head cruſſhed, he reteineth a Dragons ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, he trippeth on his héele, he caſteth foorth water after the woman and her child, he draweth downe the third part of the Starres with his tayle, he rageth horribly, and ſtormeth ſturdely, becauſe his time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pireth ſhortly: As <hi>Leuiathan</hi> in the Sea without a hooke in his noſtrels: as <hi>Behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth</hi> in wildernes, hauing no bridle in his Iawes,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 5. Iob. 1.</note> and as a Lyon rampingly he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and ſtalketh, hippeth and ſkippeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one coaſt to another, ſéeking to deuoul. And for the readier accompliſhing of his deuiſes according to his deſire, do theſe his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments worke alſo: whereby, as the head is full of poyſon, the heart is repleniſhed with malice, which boyling and raging cannot but breake out with ſuch eagrenes, that ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may the Tyger be tamed, then this miſchieuous <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſumer, and deſtroyer of men, be ſtopped from proſecuting his wood furie. Howbeit,<note place="margin">Pſalme. 2. The great crueltie of men.</note> the dweller aboue laugheth theſe mad men to ſhorne. The <hi>Scythians</hi> are ſaid to be ſo cruell and barbarous, that they eate and deuoure their parents &amp; kinſfolks when
<pb facs="tcp:17358:13"/> they be dead, in ſtead of burying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, among whome, the <hi>Eſſedonians</hi> and <hi>Maſſagetes,</hi> are chiefe: yet are they not indéed ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and cruell as theſe, who eate vp and deuoure their brethren, euen whiles they be liuing. Againſt ſuch Cormorants crieth the Lord <hi>Wo, Wo.</hi> Theſe burie not the dead,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> but the liuing: theſe deuoure and eate the bodie of Ieſus in his members, and it is to be feared, that many which come to the Table of the Lord, with pretence to eate the bodie of Chriſt, do only in this ſort féede on him, by enuying their brethren, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his members. But what gaine they by this? euen that which <hi>Iudas</hi> gained, who, when he had deuoured his maiſter, and they that ſate with him, fell headlong into an endleſſe deſtruction. They may not onely ſay, <hi>Oleum &amp; laborem perdidimus,</hi> we haue laboured in vaine, but alſo may iuſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt with <hi>Iudas</hi> and the vngodly in hell, whoſe paſſions and groanes the wiſe man thus deſcribeth:<note place="margin">Sap. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee haue weried our ſelues in the way of wickednes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: what did Pride profit vs? what gaine hath the pompe of riches brought vs?</hi> It may be aunſwered, ſo much profit as the fire in Mount <hi>Aetna,</hi> for it drieth vp
<pb facs="tcp:17358:14"/> the marrow within the bones, it macerateth the face, baniſheth all good digeſtion, hurteth the mind, and tormenteth the ſoule: for the holy ſpirit of diſcipline flieth from deceite,<note place="margin">Sap. 1.5.10.11.</note> and withdraweth himſelfe from thoughts that are without vnderſtanding. The eare of iealoſie heareth all things, and the noyſe of the grudgings ſhall not be hid, &amp;c. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayth the wiſe man:<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Be not angry for any wrong with thy neigbour, and do nothing by iniurious practiſes:</hi> Or thus (as another Tranſlation yéeldeth.) <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not euery iniury of thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 19.17.18.</note> And this is taken from <hi>Moſes</hi> lawe to the old <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thine heart, but thou ſhalt playnely rebuke him, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him not to ſinne. Thou ſhalt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge nor wayte to do diſpleaſure, or be mindfull of wrong againſt the children of thy people: but thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe: I am the Lord.</hi> This Law the Lord wrote in the hearts of his children from the beginning, and of which he expected obſeruance, when he ſayd to <hi>Cayne: Cayne, where is Abel thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſ. 50. verſe. 19.</note> And this rule obſerued <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who after many heauie iniuries receiued of hys
<pb facs="tcp:17358:14"/> bréethren, did neuertheles forget all, &amp; ſpake kindly vnto them, ſaying, <hi>Feare not now, for I will nouriſh you and your children.</hi> And King <hi>Dauid</hi> anſwered to this lawe,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25. verſe. 3.</note> who notwithſtanding that <hi>Nabal</hi> did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him churliſhly, and <hi>Doeg</hi> curriſhly reuiled him,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 19.</note> did yet at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> requeſt of <hi>Abigael</hi> put away his diſpleaſure conceiued againſt <hi>Nabal,</hi> and pardoned <hi>Shimei</hi> at his owne deſire. <hi>Stephan</hi> the Protomartyr prayed for his perſecutors, deſiring God not to charge them with that ſinne. And our Lord the true patterne of patience &amp; pietie, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus for the enuious <hi>Iewes</hi> that crucifie him, <hi>Father forgiue them, for they know not what they do.</hi> Neither hath this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſhined onely in thoſe whome the lawe of God directed, but alſo in the verie Gentiles in ſome ſort, among which <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he was exiled by the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> both forgaue them, and prayed for their good ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>Héereby the godly perſuaded themſelues,<note place="margin">The man that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth the iniurie of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may the better come to God.</note> that laying aſide all diſpleaſures, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting manifold iniuries, though it were to ſeuenty times ſeauen, as Chriſt teacheth, they might with more ſafe hearts, and quiet conſciences, approach vnto the throane of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:15"/> grace, with theſe and ſuch like petitions: <hi>Remember not the ſinnes of our youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dayes (O Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 25.</note>) <hi>Forget our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and blot our tranſgreſsions out of thy mind. Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpas againſt vs.</hi> The Lord Ieſus graunt vs the ſpirit of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and patience, to forgiue and forget the offences of our bréethren againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, <hi>Dauid</hi> in his <hi>45.</hi> Pſalme tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Church,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 45.</note> and therein euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſame, what ſhould be forgotten, that her heauenly wooer Chriſt Ieſus might be pleaſed in her:<note place="margin">Another forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more generall. Iohn. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Forget</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thine owne people, and thy fathers houſe.</hi> Therevnto counſelleth <hi>S. Paule</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Rom. cap. 12. verſe. 1.2.</hi> and in his <hi>13.</hi> Chapter of the ſame, verſes <hi>12.13.14.</hi> This is that new birth, which <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodemus</hi> with all his wiſedome is not able to conceiue: and ſo difficult and hard for the fleſhly man, which conceiueth not the things that be of God, as nothing is harder. And therefore as the valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> being in <hi>Affrica,</hi> and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that his fellowes did continually lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh with the remembrance of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, Wife and Children, which they could
<pb facs="tcp:17358:15"/> not forget, cauſed them to taſte of the Trée <hi>Lotos,</hi> (whereof, if a ſtranger eate, it is ſayd he forgetteth his owne Countrey:) ſo our moſt excellent Captaine Chriſt produceth vnto vs his holy Word, the trée of life to be taſted, eaten, and diſgeſted, with this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: <hi>Hearken ô Daughter, hearken ô Iſrael: he that hath eares to heare, let him heare: and happy is he that heareth the Word of God and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it:</hi> for by eating thereof, man liueth, he forgetteth old <hi>Adam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">To forget old Adam</note> and the fleſhly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of man, he caſteth off the ſhooe from his féete with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and draweth néere to the Lord, he meditateth on the Lawe of God day and night, and is ſatiſfied with goodnes. By this was <hi>Paul</hi> put apart from the world. This quencheth out the luſt of the fleſh, the pride of life, and loue of the world. This bringeth faith to iuſtifie man before God, and vertues to approue him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men. This harboureth men in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> whome the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous habitation of <hi>Adam</hi> could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. This draweth men from earthly <hi>Hierico,</hi> to heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadeth <hi>Iaphet</hi> to dwell in the tabernacles of <hi>Shem. Peter</hi> taſting of this,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 9.</note> goeth foorth
<pb facs="tcp:17358:16"/> at the doore, and wéepeth for his ſinne: <hi>Ruth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ruth. 2.</note> the <hi>Moabitiſſe</hi> is hereby taken from her owne countrie and brought into <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and this pearle being ſo pretious, cauſeth a man to forſake all that hee hath, to ſell all his wealth, to buy, purchace and obtayne it. The Lord graunt vs grace to bee in this poynt ſo forgetfull, that we neither remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to commit, nor dare bée ſo bold as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſinne: that wee neither dwell in the loathſome tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> nor ſo much as ſauour of the fleſhly affections of impious and vngodly men.</p>
               <p>Thus haue we ſeene, what things we are chiefly to forget and ſhut out of memorie. Now let vs beholde the true ſubſtance of memorie,<note place="margin">What to remember</note> and ſo in the end deſcend vnto this particular example of <hi>Lots</hi> wife.</p>
               <p>If wee would, that GOD in goodneſſe ſhould remember vs, and that our prayers may enter in before him,<note place="margin">Nehe. 13. verſe. 31. Ionae. 2.7.</note> as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Ionas</hi> ſayd: then muſt we not be forgetfull of that which he commaundeth to bée kept in minde. And except the Lord in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie be mindfull of vs,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.1. Geneſ. 19. verſe. 29. Pſal. 115. verſe. 12.</note> as he hath bene of old time of his ſeruants <hi>Noah, Lot, Abraham, Dauid, Ionas, Manaſſes,</hi> and others, to whome in extremitie hee ſent comfort and
<pb facs="tcp:17358:16"/> helpe, we may be compared to <hi>Sodoma</hi> and like vnto <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> wee cannot ſtande in the congregation, but bee confounded in iudgement, wee ſhall want that which may helpe vs, and finde whatſoeuer anoyeth vs: and being baniſhed from the benediction of Gods children, ſhall incurre the heauie curſe of his enemies. And a moſt fearefull thing is it to be forgotten of the Lord. For there is nothing remayning, but curſings in the towne and in the field, going out and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, in the baſket and in the ſtore, in the bodie and in the land, and in whatſoeuer is taken in hand: a ſick bodie and a faint heart, maymed members and a doubtfull minde: in the morning wiſhing for the euening:<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> in the euening deſiring the morning: venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from heauen: an hell vpon earth. Of this portion drinketh the vngodly, to whom there is no peace, ſaith the Lord, ſeeing they bee aduerſaries to the Almightie and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from his preſence,<note place="margin">Iſai. 40.</note> as cleane out of his mercifull remembrance.</p>
               <p>The faithfull children remembring theſe things with conſiderate mindes, haue reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the Lord, praying him in goodneſſe to remember them. Thus prayed <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: O Lord God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chro. 6. verſe. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>refuſe not the face of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:17"/> thine annoynted. Remember the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies promiſed to Dauid thy ſeruant.</hi> And ſo prayed that noble Captaine <hi>Nehemiah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nehe. 1.5.8. cap. 5.19. ca. 13.31.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord God of heauen, the great and terrible GOD, that keepeth couenant and mercie for them that loue him and obſerue his commandements, &amp;c. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the worde that thou commandeſt thy ſeruant Moſes.</hi> Againe, <hi>Remember me</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>in goodneſſe.</hi> That patient man <hi>Iob</hi> in his great afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cryed out vnto the Lord: <hi>Remember that my life is but a wind.</hi> And King <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> turning his face to the wall,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 20.3.</note> prayed in this manner: <hi>I beſeech thee, O Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now, how I haue walked before thee in trueth and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good in thy ſight. Baruch,</hi> in the behalfe of the captiue <hi>Iſraelites: Remember not</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the wickedneſſe of our fathers, but thinke vpon thy power, and thy name at this time.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> being moued with an excellent ſpirit,<note place="margin">Pſa. 74.20 and 137. Pſal. 119. verſe. 49.</note> ſingeth vnto the Lord: <hi>Remember thy couenant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: Remember Sion: be mindful of thy mercies, &amp;c.</hi> Finally, the condemned théefe on the Croſſe with our Sauiour, ſayth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:17358:17"/> him: <hi>Lord remember me, when thou comeſt into thy kingdome.</hi> Theſe godly deſires vttered with a faithfull heart haue not bene put backe, nor was the Lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of his loue: but as he remembred <hi>Noah</hi> and euery beaſt and all the cattel that was with him in the Arke: and as Chriſt remembred <hi>Peter, Mary, Paule,</hi> &amp; the théefe on the Croſſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 115. verſe. 12.</note> So (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of all the faithfull) <hi>The Lord hath bin mindfull of vs, and he ſhall bleſſe vs, and he will bleſſe the houſe of Iſrael, he will bleſſe the houſe of Aaron, he will bleſſe them that feare the Lord, both ſmall and great.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 105. verſe. 8.42.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath been alwaies mindfull of his couenant and promiſe that he made to a thouſand generations.</hi> Therefore let not the vngodly any longer ſay vnto the Lord: <hi>Depart from vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 21.14 Sap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>wee deſire not the knowledge of thy waies. Who is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie that we ſhould ſerue him? And what profite ſhould we haue, if we ſhould pray vnto him? For the candle of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſhall bee put out, their deſtruction haſteneth on them, their hope is as a drie thiſtle flower blowen of the winde: they leade their liues wantonly, and ſodainly they go downe into hell.</hi> And as for vs,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:18"/> let vs put our truſt in the Lord, and conſider deeply and duely to what ende the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath beſtowed on vs that excellent trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Memorie: Let vs endeuour rightlie to vſe the ſame by printing therein enough theſe fiue worthie things following. viz.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> The Lord God, and his actions both of mercie and iudgement.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> Our brethren, and that duetie wee owe them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> Our owne ſelues, what wee are, and wherevnto ſubiected.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> The finall and generall Iudgement, for which wee muſt wayt and prepare our ſelues.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> Laſtly, this memorable example of <hi>Lots</hi> wife: and this laſt do I referre to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of my generall dunſion, as the onely matter or ſubiect for the action commanded in my preſent text.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A good memorie is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</note>Now, if a man could remember with <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who was able (as <hi>Solinus</hi> reported) to call euery one of his Souldiers by his proper name, when as his hoaſt was exceeding great: Or if a man had the mindfulneſſe of that mayde which can hardly forget her attire, as <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaid: yet could we not reach herein to a ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:17358:18"/> perfection. But as for our ſelues, I feare me, we be ſo farre of, that we may rather be iuſtly compared to one <hi>Meſſala Coruinus,</hi> who albeit he was ſometime a graue Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour in <hi>Rome,</hi> and much commended by eloquent <hi>Cicero</hi> for many vertues, did yet, a two yeeres before his death become ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull, that he remembred not his owne name. Which kinde of forgetfulneſſe hath come vnto diuers other alſo, either by infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of nature, or by extreame ſickneſſe, or by dotage, or by exceſſiue cares. And would to God, that our naturall infirmities, our ſinfull agonies, our damnable dotings in blind affections, and our worldly carefulnes had not maymed vs with this maladie: then might we haue eſcaped that reproach of the <hi>Iſraelites: The Oxe knoweth his owner,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay. 1. verſ. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Aſſe the cribbe of his maiſter: but my people haue not knowne me: they haue forgotten me.</hi> Although wee cannot denie, but that we haue our earthen veſſels with <hi>Agathocles,</hi> thereby to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our originall: and with <hi>Peter</hi> haue heard the Cock crowing thriſe in our eares, to put vs in minde of things memorable: yet it is true, that we haue forgotten oftentimes that we ſhould minde, hauing our cogitations
<pb facs="tcp:17358:19"/> blinded with Satans enchantments, that ſometimes we will not heare to obey the Word of God, be it preached neuer ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. This point of folly noteth <hi>S. Iames</hi> in the man,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.23.</note> that beholding his bodily face in a glaſſe, but going his way, forgetteth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly what manner of one he was. Héeere is great forgetfulnes, from the which the Lord kéepe vs. Let vs vſe the talent lent vs, knowing that as well for that one, as for the tenne, an accompt is required, and a reckoning muſt be made: and that good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ſhall be commended with a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when the vnprofitable wretch ſhall haue his talent taken from him, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe double puniſhed.<note place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God and his Workes. Eccleſ. 12. verſe. 1.</note> Let vs remember the Lord and his meruailous works.</p>
               <p>The wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> commandeth vs to remember God, and therewith to obſerue the time conuenient, ſaying, <hi>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, whiles the euill dayes come not, nor the yeeres approach, wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them.</hi> To this duty did <hi>Moſes</hi> often incite and ſtirre vp the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who neuertheleſſe, after innumerable benefites receiued of the Lord, remembred him not,<note place="margin">Iudg. 8.34</note> but forgat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Almighty
<pb facs="tcp:17358:19"/> that begat them, &amp; God that formed them,<note place="margin">Deut. 32. verſe. 18.19.20, &amp;c.</note> which cauſed him in anger to correct them, to whet vp his glittering ſword for them, and his hand to take hold of Iuſtice againſt them, to execute vengeance on them, and to reward them that hate him. This <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing conſidered, exhorteth thus: <hi>Seeke the Lord and his ſtrength:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Seeke his face continually. Remember the meruailous works he hath done, his wonders, and the iudgements of his mouth.</hi> And thus let vs remember the goodnes of the Lord firſt generally on all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: next on his Church and holie congregation, and then on euerie particular member thereof: and conſidering the ſame, let vs aſcribe all prayſe, honor, thanks and maieſtie to him for euer.</p>
               <p>He hath not only created man,<note place="margin">The mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God</note> but in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie preſerued him, and prouided louingly for him. He maketh the Sunne to ſhine as well on the vniuſt, as on the iuſt, and giueth raine to them both, mouing all men to remember them, and without this dutie, they be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with intollerable ingratitude. But as for his Spouſe the Church, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſingeth of his louing mercies and goodnes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this manner.<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> He bleſſeth them aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly that feare the Lord both ſmall and
<pb facs="tcp:17358:20"/> great: he encreaſeth his graces towards them, euen towards them and their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for they be the choſen generation, the royall Prieſthood, the holie Ieruſalem, and bleſſed of the Lord, that made heauen and earth. And therefore this eſpeciall little flock hath the Lord wonderfully defended and kept vnto himſelfe holy, ſafe, and vndefiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. Although the holy Church is as a buſh in fire burning, yet is it not conſumed: though as a Ship toſſed, yet not ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: though as a woman trauailing, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dead; and though as a Vyne pruned, yet neuer ſterued. And as for this particular branch of the Church wherein we liue, the verie land ſauoring of the ſwéetnes of Gods mercie, we are forced to confeſſe, that the Lord hath not dealt with euery Nation as he hath dealt with vs, and do find by full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that the Nation is bleſſed which hath the Lord for their God. Laſtly, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular man ſhall duely conſider with himſelfe, and remember how many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent bleſſings he hath receiued of the Lord to the beawtifying of his body and ſoule, oh God, how ſhall he be forced to prayſe and bleſſe him in the ſame with endleſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? Aboue all, when there was neither
<pb facs="tcp:17358:20"/> ſufficiencie of wood for burnt offerings in <hi>Libanus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of God in Chriſt.</note> nor Cattell inough vppon the Mountaines of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for Sacrifices: when there was none able to treade the Wyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, nor any able man to bind the ſtrong man: when there was none able to breake downe the wall of ſeparation betwéene God and man: nor to rent aſunder the vaile of the Temple: when there was not ſo much as one ſufficient for zeale, to ſtand vp in the gappe that was open,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> to turne away the Lords diſpleaſure from man: then cauſed he his owne arme to helpe his Church, and euery member of the ſame: he ſent his owne Sonne Ieſus into the world, who to the comfort of his children, ſayth, <hi>Lo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>heere am I, to do thy will, ô Father, as in the beginning of the booke it is written of me.</hi> And this is the ſame which euen vnto me (may euery Chriſtian man ſay) is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Righteouſnes againſt Sinne, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt folly, holynes againſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fréedome againſt bondage: my righteouſnes by his reſurrection; my wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by his word; my holynes by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; my redemption by his death. Oh that men would therefore prayſe the Lord for his goodnes, and remember the wonderfull
<pb facs="tcp:17358:21"/> works wrought by him for the children of men! Oh that they would take vp the cup of Saluation with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and call vpon the name of the Lord, for all his benefites towards them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 116. Iſai. 46. Exod. 20.</note> Oh that they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to ſanctifie his Saboth. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the lawe of <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſeruant, and their ſinnes in breaking that Lawe, and thereof be aſhamed: and remember, that Ieſus Chriſt of the ſéede of <hi>Dauid</hi> is raiſed againe from the death.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. verſe. 8.</note> Such and ſo great and maruailous is the Lord in his mercies vnto his children, after the purport of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.<note place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts on his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</note> But as for his enemies, which anger him with ſtubborne rebellion, which fight vnder the banner of Satan againſt him and his children, they be ſubdued to his iudgements which on them he hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by rayning downe ſtormes and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, plagues and deſtructions, according to the effect of that communication &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deutr. 28.</hi> doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt them full of bitternes and woe, which alſo with the cauſes thereof, the Lord reiterateth in the <hi>31.</hi> of the ſame, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">Deut. 31.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>This people will riſe vp and go a whoring after ſtrange Gods of the land
<pb facs="tcp:17358:21"/> whether they go, and will forſake me, and breake the appointment which I made with them: and then my wrath ſhall waxe hoate againſt them in that day, and I will forſake them, and will hide my face from them, and they ſhall be conſumed, and much aduerſitie &amp; tribulation ſhall come vpon them: ſo that they will ſay, Are not theſe troubles come vpon me, becauſe God is not with me?</hi> How theſe Iudgements haue béene executed on the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> it is mentioned in the bookes of the <hi>Iudges, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Chronicles</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> as in many other bookes of the holie Scripture: and how the remainder of theſe things méeteth with the future Apoſtates, <hi>S. Iohn</hi> deſcrieth in the ouerthrowe of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> with the great Whoare.<note place="margin">Reuel. 18.</note> Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that men (conſidering this) would ſtand in awe and ſinne not: Kiſſe the Sonne before he be angrie, and learne of <hi>Dauid</hi> truely to proteſt in this ſort:<note place="margin">Pſal. 116. Pſal. 77. verſ. 8. &amp;c. &amp; 119.52 55.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue ſet the Lord euer before my face: I remembred the yeares of the right hand of the Lord: I remembred the works of the Lord cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly. I remembred (O Lord) thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of old, and I did meditate in all thy works, and did deuiſe of thine Actes. I
<pb facs="tcp:17358:22"/> remembred thy iudgements of old, euen the examples wherby thou declareſt thy ſelfe to be Iudge of the world, and I haue bin comforted. And I haue remembred thy Name ô Lord in the night, (in the night when other ſleepe) and haue kept thy lawe. Dauid</hi> did obſerue this, <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth the ſame to vs, and this muſt we alſo do. <hi>Remember God and his works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fiue things which moue vs to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber God.</note>There be (among other) fiue things which may moue vs, or perſwade vs the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to this dutie. The firſt whereof is, the due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the frame of the World, which a certaine Philoſopher ſaid was his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> onely Library, for in beholding the ſame, he ſawe the magnificence of Gods power, knew him therein, and kept him in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> The verie <hi>Gentiles</hi> were occaſioned héereby both to knowe and remember God, though they worſhiped him not as they ſhould,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoneth, <hi>Rom. 1.</hi> And as the Heauens declare the glorie of God, and the Firmament his handie worke, ſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent harmonie of all the creatures conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting therevnto, moueth the mind of man <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to kéepe the regiſter thereof. The ſecond thing is the perſon of man, called by the Gréekes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a little World,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:22"/> wherein is the view (as it were) of all theſe things. The auntient Philoſopher <hi>Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſtus</hi> draweth men to the knowledge and mindfulnes of God,<note place="margin">In lib. de poten. &amp; Sap. dei Dialog. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> by the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans bodie. <hi>Age fili,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpice humani corporis opificium, cuius admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione perdiſce, quis tam pulchrae imaginis conditor, &amp;c.</hi> Go to (my Sonne) looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the workemanſhip of mans bodie, by the admonition wherof learne perfitly, who is he which hath made ſo beawtifull an image. And peruſing euery part and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the body, he concludeth thus: Behold how many works of diuine Arte are in this one matter demonſtrated, euery of which is moſt ſightly and handſomly proportioned, and ſo, that euery of them yet differeth from other in his proper office. But who hath fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med theſe things? what father? what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Is it not that onely inuiſible God, which of his owne will hath done them all? And another Philoſopher ſaith, that a man hauing in his bodie ſo many ioynts &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as there be dayes in the whole yeare, is thereby put in mind of Gods goodnes, and moued to remember him continually. Héerewith, if we conſider the hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Soule, and ſo include the whole
<pb facs="tcp:17358:23"/> man, we ſhall be euen deuoured with zeale, and forced to ſing ioyfully with <hi>Dauid: O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 134.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I will feare thee: for I am fearefully and wonderfully made, marueilous are thy workes, and that my ſoule knoweth right well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the word of God written and preached vnto vs,<note place="margin">The word of God.</note> teacheth vs plainely, not onely what God is, what his will is: what he hath done, but alſo in what ſort he is to be ſerued, and how to be remembred. Without this Remembrancer, he ſaw all our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be forgetfulnes, all our knowledge, ignorance: all our wiſedome fooliſhnes: all our policies péeuiſhnes, all our ſight blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: had not the Lord giuen vs his word written not onely in the heart, but euen in Tables of ſtone, braſſe, iron, &amp;c. to remaine a Schoolemaiſter vnto vs for euer: how had the creation of the world, the making of man, the building of the woman, the placing of them in pleaſure, and cauſe of their paine bin remembred? How could the promiſe of the Lords mercie in Chriſt, the drowning of the world, the burning of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of <hi>Lot,</hi> and the puniſhment of <hi>Lots</hi> wife, bin brought to our knowledge? Yea <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe would ſoone haue forgotten
<pb facs="tcp:17358:23"/> what was written in the tables of ſtone which he brake, had not the Lord written it againe with his owne finger. Neither had the precepts and lawes of the Lord bin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred in the poſteritie,<note place="margin">Deut. 11.</note> had not the Lord commaunded the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to write them in the poſts of their dores,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> &amp;c. and the Kings to coppy them out for their inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And this charge was giuen to <hi>Iſaias</hi> the Prophet.<note place="margin">Iſai. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Now go and write it before them in a Table, and note it in a Booke, that it may be for the laſt day, for euer and euer.</hi> And of this benefite <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſayth: <hi>This ſhall be written for the poſteritie.</hi> And had not the Lord giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them his Word to be a light to their féete and pathes, a ſtaffe to ſtay them, a rule to direct them, they could not but runne a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in ignorance with the heathens, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping not onely birds, fourefooted beaſts, and corporall images, the Gods of <hi>Ekron, Baalpeor, Dagon, Aſteroth, Moloch,</hi> and ſuch, but euen the Deuill himſelfe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that commaundement of God to them:<note place="margin">Deut. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, had not the Lord commanded in his Word, the Paſchall Lamb to be eaten euery
<pb facs="tcp:17358:24"/> yeare, had not the Serpent bin lifted vp in the wildernes, had not <hi>Manna</hi> bin reſerued, had not circumciſion bin giuen to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> the lawe and ſtatutes to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they would ſoone haue forgotten altogether, and turned the ſeruice of God into Idolatrie. Finally, we at this time would ſoone forget that excellent benefit offered vs in Chriſt Ieſus, had he not willed his Goſpell to be preached, and inſtituted his Sacraments with this commandement: <hi>Do this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me.</hi> I knowe your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries be weake as the water, and ye by nature forgetfull, therefore yet do this one thing for my ſake, thereby to remember me, and declare my death till I come. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider this, and thereby remember God and his works.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, when God ſawe how often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he was ſhut out of mens minds, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when they were full and in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, he vſed often to correct and puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with manie and ſundrie aduerſities, to ſtirre them vp to conſider of his goodnes and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,<note place="margin">Affliction bringeth men to God.</note> to remember him in their beds, and to runne vnto him in their afflictions, to call vpon him in trouble, and glorifie him in his mercies. He well knew, that as the frozen
<pb facs="tcp:17358:24"/> with cold beſt thinketh of fire, the hungrie of meate, the naked of clothes, the priſoner of libertie, the condemned of pardon: ſo men be earneſt to ſéeke after God,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.</note> and to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him, eſtéeming more of his mercie in time of wrath, then of his iudgements in time of grace. As for examples, King <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> in the priſon reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth God, whome in his proſperitie he had forgotten. <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly remembreth that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lord, which before was ſhut out of memorie.<note place="margin">Pſal. 51. Exod. 2. Ier. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> in his miſerie crieth <hi>peccani: <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                  </hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> crie vnto the Lord, and <hi>Ephraim</hi> in captiuitie complayneth hartely.</p>
               <p>Thus the Lord purgeth the golde from the droſſe in the fire: thus winnoweth he the corne from the chaffe in the winde: thus ſcoureth he the ruſt from the yron on the fretting ſtone: thus driueth he the rebellious through fire and water, vntill they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with <hi>Nabuchadnezar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4.25 37.</note> that the moſt high hath power ouer the kingdomes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The polluted veſſell is with water waſhed, the raw fleſh is ſeaſoned with ſalt, the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vine muſt bee pruned with a knife: the weake ſtomackes muſt haue bitter worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood: the ſlow Aſſe a whip, the heauie Oxe
<pb facs="tcp:17358:25"/> the goade, the idle ſcholler correction, and the fleſhly Chriſtian ſower affliction. This driueth home the loſt ſonne to his father, and the wanton daughter to her mother. And herein will the Lord begin at his owne houſe, and execute this iudgement on the trees that be greene, whatſoeuer become of the drie trees. And therefore, when we feele the touch of Gods iudgements either in minde, bodie or wealth, let vs know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe, and conſider to what ende the ſame is inflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſeeke remedie thereof at the hand of God with <hi>Ephraim, Dauid, Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen.</hi> And ſo remember God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fiftly and laſtly, when the Children of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> God after their repentance,<note place="margin">Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> tryall and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient experience of the Lords Iuſtice and mercie, hee wonderfully deliuered to their great comfort, they haue a great occaſion giuen them to remember God and to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him.<note place="margin">Iudg.</note> As in the time of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> when all hope was paſt, they had a marueilous deliuerance from <hi>Madian.</hi> As in the time of <hi>Sampſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg.</note> when all hope was quailed, they had a great victorie and deliuerance from the <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> As in the dayes of <hi>Saule,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was oppreſſed by the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> againe.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Goliah</hi> was ouerthrowne, and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:25"/> deliuered. As alſo in the time of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> God gaue great victories to ſmall hoaſts agaynſt mightie Nations. A great inſtigation of them to thinke on the Lord &amp; his wonderful works. And becauſe we haue receiued great things, and obtayned wonderfull deliuerances of of the mercie of our God, let vs not forget the ſame, but ſing vnto him heartelie with ſongs of deliuerance.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing that we are willed to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> remember is, our bréethren.<note place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our brethren.</note> Firſt thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, that haue the ouerſight of vs, and which ſpeake vnto vs the word of God, as the Apoſtle chargeth,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7</note> whoſe end of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation conſidering, we muſt follow their faith. And theſe be they which ruling well, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>compted worthie of double honour. Neither muſt we neglect to beſtowe on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our temporall things, which deliuer vnto vs the Spirituall treaſure. And this is a part of that honor which we be commanded to yéeld to our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. <hi>Exod. 20.</hi> But how hardly the iudgement of man cenſureth theſe labouring perſons, with what grudgings they yéeld to them of their wealth, and with what gaineſaying the Miniſtery is furthered and relieued, all men may ſée. This is not
<pb facs="tcp:17358:26"/> to remember,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5.</note> but forget the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Wo vnto him that defraudeth the labourer of his iuſt hire whereof he is moſt worthie.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of theſe is often mentioned in the Lawe:<note place="margin">Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and ſo is that mindfulnes of our poore brother,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.</note> to whoſe néede we muſt not be gréeued to conferre.<note place="margin">Pro. 31. Tob.</note> This <hi>Berſabe</hi> alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred in her wiſe leſſon to her yong <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Prou. 31.</hi> And <hi>Tobiah</hi> to his ſonne. <hi>S. Paul</hi> chargeth the <hi>Romaines</hi> and others, to giue chéerefully to the poore:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7.</note> to do good, and forget not to diſtribute: to remember the priſoners and the poore Saints,<note place="margin">Heb. 13. Gal. 2.9. 1. Cor. 16.1. Ro. 15.26. Act. 10.</note> and for ſuch he himſelfe cauſed diuers collections to be made, and thereto laboured with his hands. He commended them much of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia</hi> and <hi>Achaia</hi> for the ſame thing. The noble <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> mindfull of his poore bréethren, did neither craue that wages he ſhould haue exacted, nor ſuffered any man elſe to oppreſſe them. But alas, there is a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cry of the poore in euery place, whoſe faces be grinded with the extortions of the wealthie, and this pitie haue they found: <hi>Am I</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Cayne) the keeper of my brother?</hi> is his ouerſight or protection committed to me? am I bound to reléeue him? Theſe perſons be not of the mind of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:26"/> Chriſt, which ſaith: <hi>Weepe not Widowe,</hi> but of the mind that <hi>Diues</hi> that rich man was, who could rather permit poore <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> to cry and dye at his gate without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. But heare that terrible ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch vnpitifull people. <hi>Math. 25. When I was hungrie yee fed mee not, when I was thirſty ye gaue me no drinke: therefore depart from me ye curſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto this dutie belongeth that, not to forget to deliuer the oppreſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of his oppreſſor. And that alſo, to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; thankefull to our bréethren that haue both laboured for vs, and comforted vs with their charities, whether they be poore or rich.</p>
               <p>This thing not onely the verie Heathens haue taught, by painting foorth their three <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Graces: but alſo the verie brute beaſts &amp; birds, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Elephant, the Storke, yea the earth inſenſible, which yéeldeth to her tiller a double reward. But alas, among vs that be Chriſtians, we oftentimes find this verified, <hi>No man remembreth the poore man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 5.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>that by his wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dome deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the Citie from the great King: Pharaohs</hi> Butler hath quite forgotten <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> though he earneſtly requeſted him to
<pb facs="tcp:17358:27"/> remember him to the King:<note place="margin">Gen. 40. verſe. 14.</note> yea the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull <hi>Sichemites</hi> haue not onely quite forgotten the goodnes of <hi>Gedeon</hi> towards them,<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.18</note> but are likewiſe conſent together with <hi>Abimelech,</hi> to riſe vp againſt him and his houſe. Thus <hi>Ioas</hi> remembred the goodnes of <hi>Iehoida</hi> the Prieſt, which had bin his only ſtay and preſeruation, in riſing vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Zacharias</hi> his ſonne and killing him.<note place="margin">2. Chr. 24.20.21.22.</note> It is great vnkindnes not to requite a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite receiued: ſo it is to forget, or not to acknowledge it: but oh moſt horrible is that vnkindnes, which recounteth good things with euill things: from this kind of obliuion the Lord deliuer vs: and a true mindfulnes of our bréethren we beſéech him to giue vs: and heerevnto may we be the better induced by the remembrance of our owne ſelues. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> This is the third thing which we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led héere to remember.<note place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our ſelues.</note> To know our ſelues, is a profitable perſwaſion to the knowledge of God, &amp; imitating of Chriſt in our duties.</p>
               <p>Heere might we be put in mind of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and condition in this land, which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, is moſt profitable, that being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by others examples, we may (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Pauls</hi> caueat) take heed we fall not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we thinke we ſtand.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> And let it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:27"/> that as the fiue talents gained fiue other, ſo is it expected, that our great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of Gods bleſſings, ſhould yéeld ſemblable thankefulnes, the want whereof bringeth dread and fearefulnes: by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the vnprofitable ſeruant, the diſobedient ſonne, the barraine fig trée, and vnfruitefull Vine: and I pray God, that in this our time of peace, we do remember not only of whome we receiue it, but alſo what belongeth to the ſame: I ayme only to that, which I ſhould with many more words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe But more particularly let euery man looke into his owne eſtate and condition, as deriued from the common condition of all men, as fold and ſubdued to ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to infirmities, miſeries, and death. To this point the Apoſtle bringeth all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when he ſaith, <hi>All men haue ſinned,</hi> and héereof tooke that generall calamitie his originall, <hi>Thou art duſt</hi> (ſayth God to <hi>Adam</hi> after his tranſgreſſion) <hi>and into duſt thou ſhalt returne againe.</hi> This is particular to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man, and this is generall to all men. Heereof is man called mortall, fleſh, graſſe, vani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, a vapour, a lyer, a corrupt feede, the child of inconſtancie, and duſt. Let men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, what man is, that they may
<pb facs="tcp:17358:28"/> not waxe proude,<note place="margin">A man doth ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member himſelfe.</note> being but duſt and aſhes. But alas, this is ſo hard a thing for them, as nothing is harder, to perſwade them ſelues what they be, what their life is. And therefore, whiles they note the condition of their tenures, whether they hold their land in fee ſimple, fee tayle, terme of life or yéeres, and accompt when their leaſes may expire, they neuer remember the condition of their owne liues, how good or euill they bee, they note not how they drawe to ende, and thinke not of death, which lingreth not.</p>
               <p>This was that notable and wiſe ſaying, which <hi>Symonides,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Simonides</note> who (as <hi>Cicero</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth firſt found out the arte of Memorie) vttered before <hi>Pauſanias</hi> the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> King at his banquet, being willed by the King to ſpeake ſomething excellent and of importance: <hi>Remember, thou art a man,</hi> ſaith he. The King hearing it, tooke it ſcornefully at the firſt: But afterward being ſhut vp in priſon and in miſerie, where alſo he dyed with famine, he called to minde that word of <hi>Symonides</hi> with great ſorrowe, ſaying: <hi>The words were in deede of great importance, but I through mad pride e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed them nothing.</hi> The like in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner read we of rich <hi>Croeſus,</hi> who in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="tcp:17358:28"/> forgat himſelfe, and what <hi>Solon</hi> had taught him, till time that <hi>Cyrus</hi> brought him to recognize his eſtate and miſerie with imminent execution of death. But <hi>Philippe</hi> of <hi>Macedonia</hi> did more wiſely prouide for his memorie, when a boy cryed to him euery day: <hi>Philippe, Remember thou art but a man.</hi> And this is common to euery one: he is a man: then mortall: then ſubiect to miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: then of ſhort life and continuance. This is the effect of <hi>Iobs</hi> deſcription of man: He hath but a ſhort time to liue,<note place="margin">Iob Man is a Pilgrim.</note> yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete with many miſeries: he commeth vp as a flower from the earth: he floriſheth a little while vpon the earth: he is cut downe and withereth in the earth. Which alſo <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> in his <hi>40.</hi> Chapter:<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ia. 1.11. 1. P. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> S. <hi>Iames</hi> in his firſt Chapter, and Sainct <hi>Peter</hi> in the firſt Chapter of his former Epiſtle do effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie applie. Man commeth from a ſinfull wombe, liueth in a wretched place, &amp; goeth to a ghaſtfull gulfe. Remember this. Olde father <hi>Iacob</hi> was moſt mindfull of this, which he alſo taught to King <hi>Pharao,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his ſonne preſented him. How old art thou? (ſayd <hi>Pharao</hi> to him) he anſwered: the whole time of my pilgrimage is an hundred and thirtie yeeres, fewe and
<pb facs="tcp:17358:29"/> euill haue the daies of my life been. He is a pilgrime. A ſimilitude neere one in effect with that of <hi>Iob</hi> likening man to a flower, and with that of the Lord calling man duſt. For as the flower is oppreſſed with many annoyes in heate and cold and of ſhort time: and as the duſt is now moyſt on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, then drie, flying in the winde, without cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyntie or conſtanines: So is the pilgrime, a ſtraunger from home, looking to his place of reſt, and euer trauayleth till he come the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, oppreſſed each while with many great daungers and miſeries.<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.10.13.</note> The fathers (ſayth the Apoſtle) all dyed &amp; confeſſed themſelues to be ſtrangers and pilgrimes on the earth; and that they ſought for a Citie hauing a foundation, whoſe builder &amp; maker is God. Some ſay, that this pilgrimage of man, is ſet forth by the example of <hi>Hagar,</hi> the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayd of <hi>Sara:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 16.4</note> who flying from <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe wandred in the wilderneſſe, and was councelled by the Angell to returne agayne to her Miſtris. But <hi>Dauid</hi> truely confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>I am a ſtraunger and pilgrime with thee, as all my fathers were.</hi> And ſo may we ſay euery one of vs. Therefore let vs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from fleſhly luſtes: therefore let vs walke and not tarie. Let vs not chooſe the
<pb facs="tcp:17358:29"/> luſtes of ſinne that hinder vs: proceede wee towards <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that holy Citie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer recognize our condition and duetie of life. Here agayne wee be warned to looke backe to our former time, what wee haue been: that wee haue been vile ſinners, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders agaynſt God, tranſgreſſors of his law, ſtraungers from the commonweale of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> and ſlaues in <hi>Aegipt</hi> vnder the tyrannie of our ſpirituall <hi>Pharao.</hi> Wee are alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to looke before vs, both on things preſent, and alſo to come. If we be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God brought into his merne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous light by Ieſus Chriſt, from bondage into freedome, from ſinne into righteouſneſſe, from the power of the deuill to the grace of God: let vs bee glad and reioyce in the Lord with continuall thankfulneſſe. If yet any be in ignorance, in blindneſſe, in ſinne, in ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornnes of heart, and thereby contemne the Goſpell: let him feare, tremble, quake, ſtand in awe of Gods iudgements: but yet not forget a timely and fruitfull Repentance. Neuer to bee merie nor ſing, nor leaue of to pray, aſke and craue pardon, vntill a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliuerance: as that birde, which being enſnared neuer leaueth crying vntill he dye or bee deliuered. And hauing future things
<pb facs="tcp:17358:30"/> before our eyes, as markes whereto men ſhoote: forget not, but remember daylie and hourelie (O thou mortall man) that <hi>Mors non tardabit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Death commeth on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng.</note> Death haſteneth on thee, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting not any ornament or treaſure ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of bodie or minde. For be thou neuer ſo fayre and well fauoured, yet with fayre <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> muſt thou dye (though happely not in that ſort) and in the kingdome of death there is no difference betweene <hi>Nireus</hi> and <hi>Therſites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nireus. Therſites.</note> of whom the Poets feigne, the one to be the fayreſt, the other to be the moſt deformed of all them that came to <hi>Priamus,</hi> pallace, or <hi>Troy:</hi> and that they ſtriuing in hell after death, who ſhould bee preferred, verdit was giuen (<hi>Menippus</hi> being the Iudge) that there was no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them. Herevnto alſo commeth, as well <hi>Diues,</hi> as poore <hi>Lazarus:</hi> aſwell wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> as fooliſh <hi>Nabal.</hi> But thou brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt of thy parents Nobilitie, and then art of gentle blood, &amp;c. What of that? Can theſe things deliuer thee? No truely. But hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken what I heare one ſay: <hi>Te, quide nobili generoſitate tuorum parentum tumeſcis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia, interrogo, &amp;c.</hi> I demaund of thée (ſaith hée) which art puft vp in pride by meanes of thy noble Parentage, whether
<pb facs="tcp:17358:30"/> thoſe thy parents bee either dead or liuing? If they be liuing, knowe this, it will not bee long ere they will dye: for death commeth on them with ſpeede. If they bee dead, then hearken what S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Aug. de. ver. Inocen. ca. vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>Reſpice eorum ſepulchra, &amp; aliorum pauperum, &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de quis dominus, quis pauper, diſcerne ſi pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vinctum à Rege, fortem à debili, pulchrum à deformi, &amp;c.</hi> Behold their Sepulchres, and the graues alſo of poore men, and ſee, who is the Lord, who is the poore man: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne if thou be able, betweene the King and the priſoner, the ſtrong man and the feeble, the beautifull and the vglie. Looke vppon their ſepulchres, and I ſuppoſe, thou mayſt not finde any great difference there, betwene the rich man and the begger, except perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture in this, that in the rich mans graue thou maiſt finde a greater ſauour of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than in the poore mans pit, for that he was fed more delicately in his life, than the poore man.<note place="margin">De. van. ſeculi.</note> The ſame <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in a certayne Sermon: <hi>Conſidera &amp;c.</hi> Marke well the groanes of them that haue lately beene your companions, what they haue béen, what they now be, and how vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie their wealth ſerued to their profite. Lo, there is nothing of them remayning to bée
<pb facs="tcp:17358:31"/> ſeene: but aſhes, which if they could now ſpeake vnto you, would vtter theſe words: <hi>O ye vaine men! to what ende doe ye ſo ouerlade your liues with vices &amp; ſinnes? Looke vpon our bones, and thereby bee aſhamed of your inſatiable couetouſnes. <hi>Quod vos eſtis, nos fuimus, &amp; quodnas fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, vos eritis:</hi> What you bee now, haue we been, and what now we bee, ſhall you be hereafter.</hi> O ye fooles, remember, that in one night,<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> that great foole mentioned in the Goſpell had his ſoule rapt from him, vncerteyne of his heyre. O man, remember, what betided that glorious Rich man which was clothed in purple:<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> death taketh holde vpon, and is throwne downe into torments, notwithſtanding the ſolemnitie of his fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralles.<note place="margin">Hug <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ma.</note> 
                  <hi>Dic mihi</hi> (ſayth another) <hi>vbi ſunt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matores ſeculi, qui tam magni fuerunt? Dic, quid eis profuit inanis gloria, breuis latitia, mundi potentia?</hi> Tell me, where be now the friends of this worlde become, which haue been of ſuch eſtimation? Shewe me, what their vaine glorie, their ſhort gladneſſe, their worldly pompe, their fleſhly pleaſures, their falſe riches profited them? What is become of their laughter? of their ſport? of their boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting? Here ſee wee the corps giuen to the
<pb facs="tcp:17358:31"/> wormes, and peraduenture their ſoules ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to perpetuall torments in another place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baruch</hi> alſo, to draw men to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the power of God vpon the proude Potentates of the earth, and to the mindful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mans condition, ſayth:<note place="margin">Baruch. 3.16.17.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Where are the Princes of the heathen and ſuch as ruled the beaſtes vpon earth? They that had their paſtime with the foules of the heauen, that hoorded vp ſiluer and gold, wherein men did truſt, and made no end of their gathering? They bee come to naught, and gone downe to hell, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men be come vp in their ſteades.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to ſhewe, that not only man, which is compared to the graſſe, but alſo that all his wiſedome and glory (which is compared to the flower of the graſſe by Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) ſhall decay:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.20.</note> hearken what S. <hi>Paule</hi> expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulateth theron. <hi>Where is the wiſe? where is the Scribe? where is the diſputer of this world? hath not God made the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world fooliſhnes?</hi> Herevnto haſteneth man, and herevnto commeth his glorie in the ende: which to remember is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie profitable for al men, as <hi>Syracides</hi> ſaith, and as <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſhed to his people.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> For
<pb facs="tcp:17358:32"/> men hauing once numbred their dayes, they be moued to ſet their mind on wiſedome, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith: and hauing conſidered the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold dayes of darkenes, they will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God the ſooner in their youth,<note place="margin">Eccles. 11.2.</note> as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> counſelleth: they will caſt away the déedes of darkenes, and put on the armour of light, as <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth, that whiles the Sunne is not darke, nor the light, nor the Moone, nor the Starres, nor the Clowdes returne againe after the rayne:<note place="margin">Eccles. 12.2.5.6.</note> before man go to the houſe of his age, and the mourners go about the ſtréete, and the duſt returne to the earth as it was. Thus muſt we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our ſelues. God graunt we forget not our ſelues. When man forgetteth himſelfe and his condition, there is none euill which he will feare to commit. God make vs mindfull of this.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the latter Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</note>Fourthly, becauſe the houre of death is vncertaine, and yet death which is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bringeth man to the iudgement, and this, as was the other, is a forceable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſtirre vs vp, to examine our ſelues, to cleare our ſelues, to prepare our ſelues with Lamps burning in our hands, and loynes girded with ſtaues to the iourney, with watchfull hearts euer liſtening when
<pb facs="tcp:17358:32"/> the Tromp ſhall ſound to the battaile: let vs in any wiſe imprint this <hi>memorandum</hi> in the tables of our mindes: <hi>Our God ſhall come, and will not be ſilent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. Mat. 25.</note> Chriſt will come in the glorie of his Father, and all the holie Angels with him, ſitting vpon the throane of his glorie. Before him ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rought all Nations to be iudged, and be ſhall diuide them one from another, as the Shepheard diuideth the Shéepe from the Goates. And we ſhall all ſtand before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſt, and giue accompts of all that we haue done.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Enoch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. verſ. 14.15.</note> the feauenth from <hi>Adam</hi> (as <hi>Iude</hi> ſayth) propheſied. <hi>Behold, the Lord commeth with thouſands of his Saincts, to giue iudgement againſt all men, and to rebuke all the vngodly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them of all their wicked deedes, which they haue vngodly committed, and of all their cruell ſpeakings which wicked ſinners haue ſpoken againſt him.</hi> This thing did that holie man thinke vpon with due expectation, which ſaid, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he did, he heard this dreadfull doome ringing in his eares, <hi>Surgite mortui, venire ad iudicium, <hi>Ariſe ye dead, come to iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </hi> Oh remember this ye that forget
<pb facs="tcp:17358:33"/> God, leaſt he take you away, and there be none to deliuer you. For in déede, when all ſtand before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſt, there ſhall be no excuſe allowed of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, to pacifie the terrible diſpleaſure of the Iudge, when the accuſations ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced againſt them. Then neither <hi>Goliah</hi> with his ſtrength, nor <hi>Croeſus</hi> with his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, nor <hi>Haman</hi> with the Kings fauour, nor <hi>Abſalon</hi> with his beawtie, nor <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> with his craftines, nor any worldly man with his vanities, ſhall be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5. Lots wife.</note>The laſt thing which I ſayd we ſhould remember at this time, is <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, which I referre to the latter part of my generall diuiſion, whereof I mind to ſpeake (and God will) in the after noone. The Lord God of his mercie graunt vs grace to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of his goodnes and mercies towards the children of men: to put diſpleaſure out of our hearts, to forget our owne people, and our fathers houſe, and to worſhip the Lord by a thankefull and reuerent remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him, of our bréethren, of our ſelues, and the iudgement prepared, that ſo with the true vſe of memorie, we may the better walke in our duties, and tend to the end of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:33"/> our deliuerie, which is to ſerue God in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and righteouſnes all the dayes of our life, before him, as <hi>Zachary</hi> ſingeth, <hi>Luc. 2.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> and that which vpon our preſeruation is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as <hi>Dauid</hi> concludeth, ſaying: <hi>He brought them foorth from Aegypt, with ioy and gladnes, that they might keepe his ſtatutes, and obſerue his lawes, Pſal. 105.45.</hi> Which, God graunt we may alſo kéepe and obſerue, to his glorie, and our comfort in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to whome with the holie Ghoſt, be all honor and glorie, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The end of the fyrſt Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <head>The ſecond Sermon. <hi>Lots Wife.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former part, we haue bin incited to the true vſe of memorie, by the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Action commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Remember.</hi> Now are we likewiſe furthered in the ſame, by the
<pb facs="tcp:17358:34"/> conſideration of the ſubiect or matter héere mentioned, namely, <hi>Lots Wife.</hi> Neither can it be impertinent to our purpoſe, if alſo we call to mind, as well <hi>Lot,</hi> as his Wife, in whome, an excellent example of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie appeareth, as of his fearefull iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts on her: for as when light and darkenes, ſwéete and ſoure, fire and water, and things contrarie are compared together, either of them is the better diſcerned from other. So by the conſideration of <hi>Lot,</hi> and then, by conferring him with his wife, and by noting the contrarie diſpoſitions and lots of them both, we ſhall in much better ſort from ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them learne that, which the holie Spirit, by reſeruing their examples for our memories, will ſuggerate vnto vs.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Lot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lot.</note> is there learned the lot of a godly man in this life, with a comfort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the godly through the mercie of God on him.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Lots Wife,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lots wife.</note> is learned the lot of the wicked in this world, with a terror vnto all backſliders and wicked Apoſtates, by the terrible iudgements of God on the wicked <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and <hi>Lots Wife.</hi> Therefore firſt beholding <hi>Lot.</hi> himſelfe, therein conſider theſe circumſtances.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:34"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> Who this <hi>Lot</hi> was.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> By what meanes he came to <hi>Sodom.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> How he behaued himſelfe in <hi>Sodom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the vngodly.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> What entertainement he found among them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> How that God loued him, and deliuered him not onely from the ſinnes, but alſo from the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the <hi>Sodomites.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>We finde in <hi>Gen. 11.27.</hi> that <hi>Lot</hi> was the Sonne of <hi>Haran,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What Lot was.</note> which was brother vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was contented (as one beléeuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord) to accompanie his Vncle <hi>Abraham,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he forſooke his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and his fathers houſe, out from <hi>Vr</hi> of the <hi>Caldees,</hi> and went ſoiourning as a Stranger into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> at the commandement of the Lord God. And héereby is he noted to be of the faithfull: as alſo more effectually by that, when being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the wicked, he neuertheles feared the Lord in all things. The Wiſeman, <hi>Sapi. 10.6.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sap. 10.6. 2. Pet. 2.</note> calleth <hi>Lot, The Righteous man.</hi> And <hi>S. Peter</hi> in his <hi>2.</hi> Chapter of his ſecond Epiſtle calleth him <hi>Iuſt Lot.</hi> Righteous in déede and iuſt both before God and man: Before God, by the forgiuenes of ſinne, through mercie and apprehenſion of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:17358:35"/> by faith. Before men, as well by his godly conuerſation and vertues, as alſo in reſpect of the wicked <hi>Sodomits,</hi> before whome, he was farre preferred. Thus was he a righteous man. And heereof it was, that he liued ſo vnſpotted among the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, vexing his righteous ſoule, that he ſaw the two Angels comming into <hi>Sodom,</hi> and roſe vp to méete them,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> that he bowed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his face to the ground, and inuited them gladly to his houſe, that he entertained them reuerently, and defended them againſt the rage of the <hi>Sodomits:</hi> that he beleeued the words of the Angels, and moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently followed them, departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Sodom</hi> without deſire to retire: that he contemned the ſinnes and ſocietie of the <hi>Sodomits,</hi> and forſaking all the truſt of the world, depended onely on the mercie of God, whom he knew to be able and willing to prouide a better habitation for him. But it is a thing worth the noting, how <hi>Lot</hi> came into <hi>Sodom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. How he came to Sodom.</note> which was vpon two occaſions, the one, by his vnhappie departure from his Vncle <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi> the other, by the fooliſh luſt of his eye in his vnhappie choice. For as we reade in <hi>Gen: 13.6.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 13.6.</note> when theſe two godly perſons <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> were greatly increaſed,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:35"/> and their flocks could not paſture together in one countrey, without conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion betwéene their ſeruants: it was the counſell of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that to eſchue that inconuenience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, being as brethren, they ſhould ſunder themſelues and their flocks one from another, and therein he did not ſticke to giue the choice vnto <hi>Lot,</hi> ſaying vnto him: <hi>Is not the whole land before thee? Depart I pray thee from me: If thou wilt take the left hand, then will I go to the right: Or if thou go to the right hand, then I will take the left.</hi> So when <hi>Lot</hi> beheld the Countrey, he perceiued that all the playne of <hi>Iordane</hi> was watered euery where: for it was (before the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrhe</hi>) as the Garden of <hi>Eden.</hi> And ſo <hi>Lot</hi> choſe vnto him all the plaine of <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> yea, he pitched his Tent euen to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> But <hi>hinc ille lachrymae,</hi> wo vnto thée ſeely <hi>Lot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lots vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie choice.</note> for whiles thou goeſt about to pleaſe thine eye, thou woundeſt thine heart, thou luſteſt for the plaine, but the buſhes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe thée: thou delighteſt in the waters of <hi>Iordan,</hi> but thou art in danger of the fire of <hi>Sodom:</hi> thou thoughteſt thou haddeſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thee into heauen,<note place="margin">Aug. de ci. Dei. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> but thou art come to the gate of hell. <hi>Sodom</hi> is faire and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:36"/> but thou muſt not taſte of their fruites,<note place="margin">Egeſippus.</note> for their Apples fall to duſt and ſcinders if thou touch them, their hearbs be hurtfull, and death is in their pot. To be plaine, there is <hi>bona terra, mala gens, <hi>a good Countrey, but a wicked people:</hi>
                  </hi> for it is truely ſayd, <hi>Gen. 13.13. that the men of Sodom were wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cauſe of ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>and exceeding ſinners againſt the Lord.</hi> This ſeparation betweene <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> came of contention and ſtrife, a cauſe of diuiſion euen among bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: this contention and ſtrife grew, of the aboundance of worldly wealth, a cauſe of much diſcord euen betweene the children of one parentage, whereof there be too many examples, beſides commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> experience. This choiſe of <hi>Sodom,</hi> came of the luſt of the eye, which enſnareth many men by the hooke of voluptuouſnes, and draweth them to hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible inconueniences, as innumerable teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, with ſemblable examples, and our daily experience do alſo witnes at the full. Beware of contention about theſe vayne earthly things, beware of a deſire to be made rich, beware of luſt of the eye, and pleaſure of the fleſh, which is in the world (as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) and is an enemy to the Lord. And if this good man could not rule himſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:36"/> neither eſchew ſome paine thereof enſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Let vs not preſume to promiſe our ſelues ſafetie and eaſe in theſe pricking thornes.</p>
               <p>Now may we ſee in what ſort <hi>Lot</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 How Lot liued there</note> liued in <hi>Sodome</hi> among the vngodly. It is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie difficult thing for a man to eſcape the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the plague, whereas the very ayre is corrupted. It is not eaſie to touch pitch, and not be therewith defiled, and to ſtand in the furnace of fire with the three children, and not haue aſmuch as a heare burned, is altogither of Gods power, and not of mans wit. <hi>Lot</hi> is in <hi>Sodome,</hi> as in a place of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as in the pit of pitch and furnace of vncleanneſſe, and yet is he there righteous among them. Yet as a Lillie among the thornes, as a childe among the Scorpions, and as a woman groning in trauaile, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth it. As a preacher of righteouſnes, he ceaſſeth not; as a Pellican in the wilderneſſe he reioyceth not: but preacheth, prayeth,<note place="margin">A cauſe of Lots ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</note> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth, and vexeth his righteous ſoule: as mooued therevnto by their great ſinnes, to beholde, how wickedneſſe was extolled, and vertues trodden downe: how right was exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and wrong dealing in price: how ſinnes did abound; and righteouſneſſe, faith and
<pb facs="tcp:17358:37"/> truth was ſcarce found: and he ſawe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell (whereof <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>Reuel. 10.</hi> to put his right foote on the Sea,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aret. in Apo.</hi> 10. verſ. 1.2.</note> but his left on the earth, when the wicked ſeemed more to flouriſh in worldly ſway and eſtimation than the godly, which had none honor at all. The Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ieremy. 9. Lam. 1.</note> liuing among the like kinde of people, was forced to vexe his minde with their vngodlineſſe, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their payne enſuing: (as it can not be but a greefe vnto a godly man to ſee the people ſo obſtinate, indurate and wicked to their own deſtruction:) and thus he brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out: <hi>Oh that my head were full of water &amp; mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſlayne of the daughter of my people!</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne: <hi>Oh that I had in the wilderneſſe a wayfaring mans cottage, that I might leaue my people, and go from them: for they be all adulterers and an aſſembly of rebels.</hi> Hereof was our Sauiour Chriſt mooued to weepe ouer <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> I would to God the godly men now had not the like occaſion giuen them to vexe their godlie mindes: but it is truely ſayd, and too truely verified: Loue waxeth colde, and the Sonne of man readie to come vpon vs: faith ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:17358:37"/> aſide and is ſcarcely found but as a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime on the earth. Tongues are bent as bowes to ſhoote foorth lyes, but for the truth they haue broken ſtrings: they proceed from euill to that which is worſe, and care not for the knowledge of God: neither brother, nor friend, nor neighbour may be truſted. This is a cauſe of confuſion and plague, the Lord of his mercie deliuer vs.<note place="margin">4 His enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynment in Sodom</note> See now (I pray you) what good <hi>Lot</hi> gayned by his being in <hi>Sodom:</hi> his deſire of pleaſures procured him payne: his hope of friendſhip, nothing but afflictions. Firſt, being among the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lot had many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites.</note> he was taken priſoner with his wife and all his ſubſtance, together with the Kings of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> by <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphel</hi> King of <hi>Shinar, Arioch</hi> King of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſar, Chedarlaomer</hi> King of <hi>Elam,</hi> and <hi>Tidal</hi> King of the Nations, in great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life. Well, the vngodly may bée ſometimes fauoured by the meanes of the godly men among them: but this is ſure, that the godly can haue no good by ioyning hands with the vngodly, or being among them. The tares may be ſuffered for a time, becauſe of the corne: but in the meane while, the corne is annoyed by the growing vp of the tares with it. Therfore <hi>Pharaos</hi> Court
<pb facs="tcp:17358:38"/> is no place for <hi>Moſes</hi> to wayt in, nor <hi>Puti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phars</hi> houſe for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to ſerue in, nor <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazars</hi> feaſt for <hi>Daniel</hi> to banquet in, nor <hi>Nabucadnezars</hi> glorie for <hi>Sidrach</hi> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in, nor the open land for <hi>Dina</hi> to gad in, nor the high Prieſtes pallace for <hi>Peter</hi> to come in, nor <hi>Sodom</hi> a Citie for iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> to inhabite in. It is commaunded: <hi>Come out from Babilon my people, leaſt ye be pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with their ſinnes, and ſo take parte of their plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although we learne (as afterward it ſhall be declared) that the baniſhing hence of the righteous, haſteneth deſtruction on the reſt;<note place="margin">The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly can not abide the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</note> yet cannot the vngodly haue quiet mindes vntill they haue extirpated and roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out al the godly from among them. The ſame wee ſee in this example of <hi>Lot,</hi> who could not enioy the benefite of any <hi>Superſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas</hi> among the Citizens of <hi>Sodom.</hi> He did not only vexe his righteous ſoule there with beholding their ſinnes, but alſo he was viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly oppreſſed with their crueltie. They ruſhed in vpon him ſaying: <hi>Thou art come hether,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>but as a ſtraunger among vs, and wilt thou bee our Iudge?</hi> Thou art no towne borne child, nor citizen of ours, nor of this countrie, thou art not of our ſocietie and
<pb facs="tcp:17358:38"/> companie, nor of our conditions: we did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beare thee ſuch good will to make thee a Iudge ouer vs, or to bee tryed by thy deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination: no, but wee will deale worſe with thee, then with theſe men, whom thou har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreſt.</p>
               <p>Oh good <hi>Lot!</hi> couldeſt thou ſo long time abide there, where thou couldeſt neuer bee welcome? What gayneſt thou among ſuch vngodly perſons? Thou mayſt ſay: Only this, a triall of my patience and pietie: An experience of the great might and mercie of the Lord. Such is <hi>Lots</hi> enterteynment in <hi>Sodom.</hi> God graunt that his children may be betimes warned to take heed of ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteyners: and that wee our ſelues be not contented to yeeld hatred vnto them, that deſerue to be welcome among vs.</p>
               <p>Another affliction had this good man,<note place="margin">Lots own wife was an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him.</note> which peraduenture did touch him neerer, namely by this, that his owne wife which lay in his boſome, and ſhould of all other be a comfort vnto him, became a griefe and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiue to his heart.</p>
               <p>It was no ſmall griefe to <hi>Dauid,</hi> that his owne ſonne, ſought after his life: And our Sauiour proteſteth with no little ſorow of ſoule, that the ſame which eate bread
<pb facs="tcp:17358:39"/> with him, lifted vp his heele agaynſt him. And it may bee, this godly man would not haue ſtayed ſo long in <hi>Sodom,</hi> had not his wife been a vehement cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vnequall yokes.</note>Here then let vs learne to take heede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what yokes ye ſubmit your ſelues, and with what wiues ye ioyne.<note place="margin">Ioſ. 24.</note> It was ſayd of the women of the Nations: they will be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, ſnares, prickes in your eyes, and whippes on your ſides: they will allure you, ſeduce you, drawe you to Idolatrie. Did not <hi>Salomon</hi> the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinne in theſe things?<note place="margin">Nehe. 13.24.</note> Did not the daughters of men defile the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God?<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> Was not <hi>Iezabell</hi> a pricker forward of <hi>Ahab</hi> to euery miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe? Did not <hi>Saule</hi> prouide <hi>Michol</hi> to be a ſnare vnto <hi>Dauid?</hi> and did ſhe not mocke at him openly? Did not <hi>Iobs</hi> wife greeue him in the bitterneſſe of his heart? Was not <hi>Eſau</hi> blamed for taking wiues of the <hi>Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites,</hi> a griefe of minde to old <hi>Iſaak</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beccha?</hi> Therefore <hi>Iacob</hi> was ſtraitly charged by his parents to eſchew ſuch wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſware his ſeruant, that he ſhould not take a wife for <hi>Iſaak</hi> of theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and a lawe was ratified by <hi>Moſes</hi> to that ende.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> This is <hi>Paules</hi> charge: <hi>Beare not the yoke with Infidels.</hi> Let vs take
<pb facs="tcp:17358:39"/> heede then of vnequall matches. The man which is vnwilling to be drowned, doth not caſt himſelfe deſperatly into the Sea: and it is agaynſt nature for a perſon to ſeeke comfort of that which by nature yeeldeth corraſiues and griefes. <hi>Lots</hi> wife being by nature euill, could not do any good to her huſband in all her life. A great affliction.</p>
               <p>This thing alſo is general, that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereſoeuer they come, ſhall be as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnto the worldlings, as water to the fire, as <hi>Lot</hi> was to <hi>Sodom.</hi> Chriſt telleth this playnlie: <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my names ſake.</hi> And <hi>Iohn</hi> his holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayth: <hi>Marueile not my brethren, though the world hate you.</hi> Doth not <hi>Cain</hi> enuie <hi>Abel?</hi> Is not the olde world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <hi>Noah? Iſmael</hi> agaynſt <hi>Iſaak? Eſau</hi> agaynſt <hi>Iacob?</hi> Doth not <hi>Saule</hi> enuie <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> for his victorie? Do not the Lords of <hi>Babilon</hi> hate <hi>Daniel</hi> for his pietie? Do not all the Nations conſpire together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Yea more yet: though <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> deuoureth <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> deuour <hi>Ephraim,</hi> yet do not they both ioyne hand in hand to deuoure <hi>Iuda</hi> the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance? As <hi>Pilate</hi> agaynſt <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> agaynſt <hi>Pilate,</hi> but both of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:17358:40"/> Chriſt? what concord betweene fire and water? what peace betweene <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial,</hi> may be found? But yet, why doth the world thus hate the children of God, whom they haue rather cauſe to loue? The children of God be brethren at amitie in themſelues, whoſe ſocietie Satan ſéeketh to diuide, that his owne arme may be the ſtronger, and that one houſe may fall vpon another. They be the redeemed from the earth, &amp; from the power of darknes, whome he ſeeketh againe to drawe vnto him: they follow the Lamb whereſoeuer he goeth, to the great griefe of Satan: they be not of the world, but choſen out of the world, therefore they be hated, but haue the worldlings any iuſt cauſe of hatred giuen them? no truely, for as Chriſt was hated without a cauſe of them that ſhould haue rather loued him, ſo are his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet they alleadge cauſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for themſelues, whoſe imaginations, the Wiſe man deſcrieth in his <hi>2.</hi> Chapt. of the booke of Wiſedome:<note place="margin">Sap. 2.</note> where he telleth, that the vngodly being not fully perſuaded of a better life after this, and therefore minding to take their fill of pleaſure heere in deſpight of Gods threatnings, &amp; in contempt of his promiſes, without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troulment or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction
<pb facs="tcp:17358:40"/> of the righteous, which can not but ſpeake againſt them, they thus reſolue and conclude againſt the righteous, <hi>Let vs oppreſſe the poore man that is ſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> Will ye oppreſſe, nay rather, deale iuſtly. Will ye hurt the poore? nay rather helpe him. Will ye do violence to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man? nay rather do him good. But ye will not be reſtrained: ye will oppreſſe him, and why? he is not for our profit: he is contrary to our doings: he checketh vs for offending: he accounteth vs tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of diſcipline: he boſteth himſelfe of the knowledge of God: he ſaith he is Gods ſonne: he is made to reproue our thoughts: it greeueth vs to ſee him: his life is not like other mens: his wayes are of another ſort: he accounteth vs as baſtards: he abhorreth our wayes: he commendeth only the latter end of the righteous, therefore we will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin him with rebukes and torments, we will condemne him to a ſhamefull death. Alas ye miſerable caitiffes, be theſe your profound arguments? Indéed theſe beſeeme him that ſaith in the pride of his heart, <hi>Sic volo, ſiu iubeo, ſtat pro ratione voluntas: <hi>I will haue it ſo, ſo I commaund it to be done, my will is an argument forcible
<pb facs="tcp:17358:41"/> ynough.</hi>
                  </hi> This is the manner of dealing of the worldlings againſt the righteous: So is <hi>Lot</hi> entertained. Now ſéeing the caſe thus ſtandeth,<note place="margin">The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are to ioyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in loue.</note> oh how ready ſhould the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be to ioyne together, and liue in concord together? a thing both godly and profitable, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſingeth, <hi>Ecce quam bonum, &amp;c.</hi> for the houſe is not deſolate, nor the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome confounded, where loue and concord dwelleth and raigneth. It is good for birds of one flight to flye together, chickens of one hen to couch together, ſhéepe of one fold to flock together, ſtrings of one inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſound in harmonie together, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one bodie to ioyne together, and Chriſtians of one calling to loue together, as ſonnes of one father, brethren of one Chriſt, and Saints of one God. This is expreſſely commaunded by Chriſt: this is the badge or recognizance whereby we be knowne, and heereby we be aſſured of our tranſlation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith. And the Apoſtles ſpeaking heereof, lay oftentimes our Sauiour for a patterne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, who commaunded his Diſciples to loue together, as he had loued them: that was (as one noteth) <hi>Veraciter ſine ſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one: prudenter ſine corruptione: temperanter
<pb facs="tcp:17358:41"/> ſub Dei dilectione: generaliter ſine exceptione.</hi> That is, without ſimulation truly: without corruption wiſely: vnder the loue of God temperately: without exception generally. Heere is not taught the loue of <hi>Cayne</hi> to <hi>Abel,</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> of <hi>Iudas</hi> to Chriſt: but heere is the loue of <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Ionathas,</hi> of <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi,</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Barnabas,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Iohn.</hi> Againe, heere is taught to loue not the errors, but the vertues of our brethren, to hate the ſinne with loue of the perſon: to loue not for wealth, nor fauour, nor ſtrength: but for that he is thy brother a Chriſtian. Yet ſo as this loue muſt not exceede the loue of our God, whome aboue all things we muſt loue: that in regard of that, we muſt euen forſake all other things which may hinder vs from the ſame. For <hi>whoſoeuer loueth either father or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wife or children, yea, or his owne life, more then me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is not worthy of me:</hi> heerein then is temperance learned. Let vs loue hartely, but yet in the feare of God: and vnder his loue, yet ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently, as we may honor God in our loue. Laſtly, we are taught by this rule, to loue generally, I ſay not all men alike: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God in mercie maketh his ſunne to
<pb facs="tcp:17358:42"/> ſhine aſwell on the euill, as on the good: and ſo they féele as it were the beames of Gods loue, whereof they be moſt vnworthy: yet hath he euer had an eſpeciall loue to his own children. The houſhold of faith muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the worldlings, as <hi>Iacob</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Eſau, Iſaac</hi> before <hi>Iſmael, Abel</hi> before <hi>Cayne, Dauid</hi> before <hi>Saule, Salomon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore <hi>Abſolon, Iohn</hi> before <hi>Iudas,</hi> but I ſpeake heere only of the brethren. This rule is enioined to the flock vnder one ſhepheard, to loue and embrace, of what nation, kinred, toong or ſexe ſoeuer they be. Thus let vs loue without exception, ſo ſhall we yeeld and obey as good childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our heauenly father: ſo ſhall we ſhew our ſelues his ſchollers: ſo ſhall we aſſure election to our ſelues: ſo ſhall we be ſtrong in our ſelues: ſo ſhall we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our enemies on euery ſide, and ſhine as lights in the middeſt of a crooked genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thus haue we ſeene the entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now are we to conſider, how that this good man,<note place="margin">5 The deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of Lot.</note> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the hatred of his Citizens, obteined the loue and mercy of the Lord, through whom, not only himſelf was wonderfully deliuered from deſtruction, bu alſo his aduerſaries for a time fared the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:17358:42"/> for his preſence.<note place="margin">P. Mart. in Gen. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> It may be that now the prayer of <hi>Abraham</hi> had his effect in this, that God deſtroyeth not <hi>Lot</hi> with <hi>Sodom.</hi> For it is ſaid, that God remembring <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (and therein his prayer) tooke <hi>Lot</hi> out of the middeſt of the ouerthrowe. Heereof it was, that God was mercifull vnto him, and therefore ſent his Angell to deliuer him: yea and when he delayed, the Angell did euen perforce conſtraine him to flie. But ſo much the rather, in that <hi>Lot</hi> was alſo a righteous man: whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> argueth (no doubt) among the ſemblable examples, <hi>I neuer ſawe the righteous forſaken.</hi> And why <hi>Gen. 18.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> ſhould not the Iudge of all the world do according vnto right? and who is righteous? euen <hi>Lot,</hi> in that by his faith he obteined mercie: and therefore he is ſaued (though by nature ſinfull) yet by the mercie of the Lord made righteous. But fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what other example might <hi>Dauid</hi> gather this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance? was not <hi>Noah</hi> ſaued from peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing by water, with his family, when all the world was ouerwhelmed? was not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> preſerued in a ſtrange land &amp; was not <hi>Iſaac</hi> wonderfully preſerued by the Angell, when his father held vp the knife to haue killed him &amp; was not <hi>Iacob</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:43"/> Lords prouidence, heere is his fault &amp; fall: ſuch is mans wiſedome, and therevnto it tendeth: a note of diſgrace in ſo godly a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But God is yet mercifull vnto <hi>Lot,</hi> yea and ſpareth for a time <hi>Sodom</hi> through him. And heere obſerue, that whereas the Lord ſtayed the wrath of his rod from his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, till time that <hi>Lot</hi> was gone out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> leaſt happely the righteous had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed among the wicked, which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, as <hi>Abraham</hi> praied. So do we ſee that commandement of the tares heere verified, <hi>Let them yet alone, leaſt whiles ye weed out them, yee pluck vp alſo the corne.</hi> The Angels ſaid plainely to <hi>Lot,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they willed him to haſten vnto <hi>Zoar, We can do nothing vntill thou be come thither.</hi> And this is a generall thing, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God determineth to extirpate and roote out Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">When good men be taken hence, plagues may be feared to follow.</note> Kingdomes, and people, he firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the godly from among them, and leauing only a confuſed heape of vngodlie perſons, a free paſſage is giuen to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his iudgements. When we ſee therefore that good men do ſlide from vs, let vs feare of a iudgement enſuing, &amp; with repentant hearts turne vnto the Lord, and craue mercie in time conuenient. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:17358:43"/> 
                  <hi>Ezechiel</hi> telleth, <hi>that when the Lord could find no zealous man among them Ezech. 22.31. he powred out his wrath, and conſumed them. Iſaiah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa 57.1.</note> ſaith, <hi>that the righteous men do dye, and be taken away from the euill that commeth after them.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> witneſſeth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>that the godly men be gone, and the wrath of God recompenceth the remaynder.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples héereof we haue many. Among which we remember, that when <hi>Noah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Noah.</note> was gone from the world, and was encloſed in the Arke, the water foorthwith fell downe vpon the world, and drowned it. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> King <hi>Hezekiah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hezekiah.</note> was layde to his Fathers in peace, the plague fell downe vpon <hi>Iuda,</hi> which the Lord had by promiſe reſtrained all the time of his life. The like in effect is mentioned of <hi>Ioſias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſias.</note> Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles being departed from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and not one left there, but counterfeit <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſt and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</note> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious euill ſinners, all the plagues that tended to the vtter deſtruction of that City, immediatly followed,<note place="margin">Matth. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy houſe is left de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, for yee ſhall not ſee me hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth, &amp;c.</hi> So heere, <hi>Lot</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lot.</note> the righteous man, being gone out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the Lord rained vpon them fire and brimſtone from
<pb facs="tcp:17358:44"/> heauen,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciu. dei. <hi>21</hi> Solinus. Egeſippus.</note> and conſumed them all, and their Countrie, as many auncient Teſtimonies, eſpecially the holie Scripture reporte.</p>
               <p>The conſideration hereof might moue euen the vngodly, to wiſh for and deſire the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; gladlie to enterteyne and reteyne the ſocietie of righteous <hi>Lots</hi> among them. And when they perceiue them departing, to dread great iudgements im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.</note> as the daughter of old <hi>Eli</hi> did, who hearing that the Arke of God was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> cried out in great feare: <hi>Now is the glorie gone from Iſrael, for the Arke of God is taken away!</hi> And thus much for the perſon of <hi>Lot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now are wee come to the view of <hi>Lots</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wife.<note place="margin">Lots wife.</note> Wherein wee are to conſider: Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> what ſhe was. Secondly, what ſinnes are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> chiefly noted in her. Thirdly, what was her plague or puniſhment.</p>
               <p>This woman by all likelihood was of the <hi>Cananites,</hi> but farre vnlike the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> that cryed after Chriſt for her daughter. And it may eaſely bee gathered that <hi>Lot</hi> maried this woman either in or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Sodom,</hi> whereas he pitched his tent: partly for that wee do not finde in the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that ſhe came thether with him, as <hi>Sarai</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:44"/> did with <hi>Abraham:</hi> partly for that ſhe had ſuch an earneſt deſire to ſtay, and dwel there among them. And it is true,<note place="margin">Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites bee mixt with the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</note> that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the commaundement of God to the contrarie, ſome <hi>Canaanites</hi> are not onely dwelling, but alſo ioyning vnto them of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> which cannot do them any good, but euill as long as they liue. As long as the godly man ſoweth corne in this world, will the enuious man caſt in his tares among. While the net is in the Sea, the bad fiſhes wil be taken together with the good: whiles the Muſtard ſeede groweth vp to a tree, the birds of all ſorts will rowſt vnder the ſame. The beaſtes of al kinde will be found in the Arke, and <hi>Cham</hi> wil couch betwene <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Iaphet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 10.</note> and growe to a mightie nation to diuide their Tabernacles aſunder: that now the Lords flocke, in reſpect of all the reſt, is called <hi>little.</hi> As if the Lord had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of all birdes one Doue, of all beaſtes one Sheepe, of all trees one Cedar in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus: of all pittes, one Riuer <hi>Iordan:</hi> of all hilles, one <hi>Sion:</hi> of all people, one <hi>Iſrael:</hi> of al Cities, one <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> &amp; out of all <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Lot:</hi> but not <hi>Lots</hi> wife. As all the world to <hi>Noah:</hi> all <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſtes to <hi>Elias,</hi> all the rebellious <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to <hi>Ioſhua.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſ. 24</note> All
<pb facs="tcp:17358:45"/> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to Chriſt and his Apoſtles. So is <hi>Sodom</hi> to <hi>Lot,</hi> yea and with them his owne wife. This is not <hi>Sarah</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> nor <hi>Rebeccah</hi> to <hi>Iſaak,</hi> nor <hi>Heſter</hi> to <hi>Aſhuerus,</hi> nor <hi>Suſanna</hi> to <hi>Ioachim,</hi> nor <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> nor <hi>Mary</hi> to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph:</hi> but here is ſo heauie a yoke, as good <hi>Lot</hi> could not well beare, and ſuch a burden as he was not able to bring forth from <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> to <hi>Zoar.</hi> Here is a curſt <hi>Xantippe</hi> to a learned and patient <hi>Socrates:</hi> here is a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring <hi>Annah</hi> to an holie <hi>Tobiah,</hi> yea more yet than that: here is a diſdaynfull and mocking <hi>Micholl</hi> to a zealous <hi>Dauid,</hi> and a curſed woman to a bleſſed <hi>Iob.</hi> But wee may note in her ſome particular ſinnes, and eſchew them the better by the conſideration of her euill ſucceſſe for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Firſt we note in her infidelitie.<note place="margin">1 Infidelitie</note> For ſhe beleeued not the words of the Angels which ſayd: <hi>We be come hither to deſtroy this place.</hi> And herein ſhe ioyned hands with all her kinne in that citie, who eſteemed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of <hi>Lot,</hi> touching the wordes of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as fables vainely inuented: or ſhee thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God would haue ſpared ſo beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull a thing, notwithſtanding the Angels words. So <hi>Thomas</hi> was incredulous, and
<pb facs="tcp:17358:45"/> would not beleeue the words of them which ſayd, they had ſeene Chriſte after his death, But yet <hi>bleſſed are they, which haue not ſeene, and yet haue beleeued. Sarah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> that woman is commended for her fayth by the Apoſtle. The wife of <hi>Manoah</hi> alſo is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in that ſhee beleeued the Angels words to her.<note place="margin">Iudg. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Anna</hi> alſo the mother of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, Rahab, Ruth, Mary, Martha, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, Damaris,</hi> and other like women are for their faith prayſed: but <hi>Lots</hi> wife is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed by her vnbeleefe.</p>
               <p>This is the ſubtiltie of Satan:<note place="margin">Satans craft to take away a mans faith.</note> firſt to pull out faith from mans heart, which being once gone, he knoweth that man is neither able to reſiſt him, nor to quench his fierie dartes. He doth therein as the Rauen, which firſt picketh out the ſheepes eye, and afterward deuoureth his bodie: And faith is in a man, the eye of the ſoule. Satan knoweth, that faith is the pillar whereon our building ſtandeth. Therefore he ſhaketh it to caſt downe our building. He knoweth that faith is as a Tower which giueth vs two aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages agaynſt him: namely, to defende our ſelues thereby from him, and to caſt out from thence the ſtrokes of thundring Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to annoy him. Therefore he firſt
<pb facs="tcp:17358:46"/> aymeth to our faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. Ephe. 6. 1. Pet. 1. Rom. 9. 1. Cor. 10. Rom. 11.</note>The Apoſtle ſhewing the commodities of faith by the examples of <hi>Abraham, Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ak, Iacob, Sarah,</hi> and other Saincts, doth thereto oppoſe the infidelitie of ſuch as haue thereby purchaſed iuſt paynes for recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence. <hi>Adam</hi> by his vnbeleefe, with <hi>Eua,</hi> were caſt out of <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting faith could not come into the land of promiſe, but periſhed in the wilderneſſe: he that beleeued not the Prophet, was trodden on in the gate of the Citie: <hi>Zacharie</hi> was dumbe becauſe he did not beleeue the worde of the Angell: the Apoſtles were checked for their vnbeléef, and <hi>Lots</hi> wife is plagued. The world is reprooued for ſinne by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Io. 16.</note> becauſe they beleeue not: as if vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this one ſinne al other ſinnes were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and well worthie: for without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, ſeeing whatſoeuer is done, is ſinne. The <hi>Iewes,</hi> by their vnbeleefe, were not onely vnworthie that Chriſt ſhould work any myracle among them in his owne countrie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but alſo they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated the fauour of God from them and their children. This is if grieuous ſinne.</p>
               <p>Let vs take heed of vnbeleefe and eſchew the payne therof, by a perfect faith in Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:17358:46"/> Let vs beleeue the voyce of the Angell: let vs hearken vnto our greate Archangell Chriſt and his word preached by his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that wee may beleeue: for faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by hearing, and faith hath more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, than I am able to expreſſe at this time. When Satan deſired to ſift vs as wheate, Chriſt prayed that our faith might not fayle. The Lord therefore helpe our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, and encreaſe our faith in vs euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that thereby we may haſten from <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> with righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> and not ſtay, or turne thether agayne, to periſh with his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous wife.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in her is noted the ſinne of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.<note place="margin">2 Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> 
                  <hi>Lot</hi> obeyed the voyce of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and departed from <hi>Sodom,</hi> without retyre or looking backe: but ſhe diſobeyed that voyce in looking backe. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, for ſhe beleeued not. For obedience is not expected from infidelitie, no more than the ſtanding of an houſe without a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſweete fruite to growe on the tree that hath a bitter roote. She would not come forth to <hi>Zoar</hi> to ſaue her felfe there. She looked back to <hi>Sodom.</hi> Though obedience be better than Sacrifice, as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſayd to <hi>Saule,</hi> &amp; to hearken is better than the blood
<pb facs="tcp:17358:47"/> of Goates, and diſobedience is as the ſinne of witchcraft: yet ſhe obeyeth not, ſhe hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth not, but rebelleth. Although it was commaunded by the Lord, enioyned by the Angell:<note place="margin">Gen. 19. Deut. 28.</note> and obedience hath a promiſe of the beſt thing in the lande, and diſobedience a commination of plagues which ſurely bee performed, and that not the hearers of the lawe be iuſtified but the doers: yet is ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient. Would to God, the moſt part in theſe dayes did not followe her therein. Take heede of the iudgements thereunto belonging. <hi>Saule</hi> for diſobedience is reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his kingdome taken from him. The man of God was ſlayne of a Lion,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15 1. Kin. 13.</note> becauſe he did eate bread in the old Prophets houſe, contrary to Gods expreſſe commandement. The good King <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> in that he obeyed not the Lord, ſpeaking out of the mouth of <hi>Neco</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet a wicked King, was ſtriken that he dyed. The fathers in the wilderneſſe periſhed through diſobedience, yea and many that did things with a good intent, yet diſobediently, were ſurely repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and puniſhed. <hi>Vſſah</hi> touched the Arke as it was falling, with entent to ſtay it vp: it apperteyned not to him, therefore is he ſtriken. <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> the ſonnes of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:47"/> 
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> tooke ſtraunge fire in their Cenſors, thinking they did well, but being contrarie to the commaundement, they haue therfore a grieuous puniſhment. In theſe, yea euen in theſe perſons was this ſinne puniſhed. But what of that? Shall we then thinke to eſcape vnpuniſhed for the like, yea and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter breaches of Gods holie commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?<note place="margin">Heb. 10.20 29. Deut. 19.15.</note> If he that deſpiſeth <hi>Moſes</hi> law dyeth without mercie vnder two or three witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; of how much greater puniſhment ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye ſhall he bee worthie of, which hath troden vnder foote the Sonne of God, and hath counted the bloud of the Couenant, wherein he was ſanctified, an vnholy thing: and hath done deſpight vnto the Spirite of grace?<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The time is come that iudgement beginneth at the houſehold of God: and if it begin there, what ſhall be the end of them that beleeue not the Goſpell? I begin</hi> (ſayth the Lord) <hi>to plague the Citie whereon my name is called,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 25.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and thinke you, I will ſuffer you to eſcape? No, ye ſhall not go quite.</hi> Take heede then of this ſinne of <hi>Lots</hi> wife. Wee do reade of other women, which haue gotten both fauour and commendation by obedience to GOD and their owne huſbands; but <hi>Lots</hi> wife looſeth
<pb facs="tcp:17358:48"/> all good reporte, yea her life and health too, through diſobedience.</p>
               <p>The third fault we note in her, is Pride:<note place="margin">3 Pride.</note> this thing did the deuil ioyne to infidelitie &amp; diſobedience of <hi>Euah;</hi> who would willingly be as God. So this woman aſpiring aboue degree, therby contemneth the ſimple eſtate of her owne huſband, and the worde of the Lord. Oh how much better had Chriſtian humilitie beſeemed her! It is the beſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a faithfull perſon. <hi>Abraham</hi> was beautified therewith, when comming before the Lord, he accompted himſelfe vile duſt and aſhes, vnworthie to ſpeake vnto his Maieſtie. This <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo had, when he daunced bare before the Arke, though <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choll</hi> his owne wife diſdained him thereat. This vertue did Chriſt himſelfe embrace, who oftentimes fell on his face to the earth, when he prayed, yea and yeelded himſelf to the great contempt of the Croſſe. Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie lifteth that vp into heauen, which pride aſſayeth to caſt downe in hell. The humble and lowe degree of <hi>Mary</hi> the Lords hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayd is eſteemed, and ſhe accompted bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: the poore Publican is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Dauid</hi> obteyneth mercie: but the proude Phariſte <hi>Antiochus, Senacherib, Herod,</hi> and other
<pb facs="tcp:17358:48"/> proude perſons haue been caſt downe. <hi>Lots</hi> wife in her pride diſdayned the vocation of her huſband, ſhe contemned the Countrie whereinto he was going from <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſhe thought ſcorne to make ſuch a chaunge, and to endure in ſteede of pleaſure affliction: for delicate fare, hunger and colde: for eaſe, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle: for fine apparell, Camels hayre: for ſeeled houſes, Caues of earth: for Iuorie beddes, the harde ſtones, or graſſe in the fieldes: in ſteede of companie, ſolitarineſſe: for mirth, mourning: and ſorrowes for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. She diſliked now after ſo many weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie pleaſures in <hi>Sodom,</hi> to become as a Pellican in Wilderneſſe, as a doue alone mourning, as the ſparrowe on the houſe top ſorrowing. She could not abide that, for there is nothing more contrary to the croſſe of Chriſt, than Pride. <hi>Except ye humble your ſelues and become as children, ye cannot enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> ſayth Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Pride bringeth men with ſpeede to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> yeeldeth confuſion, ſhame and fall. I would to God there were not found too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poſſeſſed with this deuil among vs, who, albeit they bee called Chriſtians, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:17358:49"/> méekeneſſe they ſhould followe, do yet in the pride of their hearts diſdaine ſimple Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and his word, and that were it not for the loue of worldly eſtimation and wealth, would euen openly contemne the profeſſion of humble Ieſus. The Lord ſtop the great inconuenience of this ſinne, to the caſting downe of proud <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his members, that the glorie of Ieſus Chriſt might be the better embraced euen in humilitie.</p>
               <p>Another fault we note in this vngracious woman: that is, wanton and worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,<note place="margin">4 Worldly pleaſure.</note> which was of force to withſtand her proceeding. <hi>Sodom</hi> was a pleaſant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, as the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> ſo well watred, and the Apples and fruites therein moſt beautifull to the eye.<note place="margin">Video me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boque, &amp;c</note> And hereon Appetite tooke occaſion to contend with reaſon, and in her preuayled, that with <hi>Medaea</hi> ſhe could now diſpute, and thus reſolue: <hi>yet wil I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my pleaſures, be they neuer ſo noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and eate theſe apples be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo venimous, though I ſee that which is wholſomer and cannot but commend it.</hi> Theſe ſnares doth Satan caſt before the hungrie foules to take them, &amp; merily ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when he deceiueth. The <hi>Syrenes</hi> ſing
<pb facs="tcp:17358:49"/> ſweetly, the <hi>Lamaei</hi> ſhine beautifully, the Serpent ſuggeſteth ſubtiltie, and the deuill promiſeth al the glorie of the world to them that worſhip him.</p>
               <p>But they reaſon for themſelues and will coyne excuſes, although he that had maried a wife had none excuſe at all: Shall I aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don worldly pleaſures? I am yet but a yong man. Shal I not haue a wanton eye? I am but a girle. Shal I looſe the aſſurance of my delights here, and truſt to an vncerteyntie? Take heede, O yong man:<note place="margin">Eccle. 11.</note> and knowe that an accompt ſhall bee called of thy youthfull yeeres: and a payne will enſue theſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. The Apples of <hi>Sodom</hi> bee fayre to behold; but touch them, and they fall to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: and the ſtinging <hi>Hydra</hi> lyeth vnder the golden ſwarth. Remember, that <hi>Heuah</hi> loſt the true pleaſures of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing her pleaſant appetite. <hi>Eſau</hi> for a meſſe of pottage, and his worldly pleaſure, did loſe both the birthright and bleſſing: the man that had wedded himſelfe to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, could not enioy the benefite of the mariage feaſt: and <hi>Lots</hi> wife for the wanton pleaſures of <hi>Sodom,</hi> loſt the ſaftie of <hi>Zoar,</hi> and turning from heauen, was deuoured of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:50"/> hell. Remember what our Lord ſayd: <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoever loveth either father or mother, wife or children, or any thing in the world more than me, is not worthie of me.</hi> And remember what father <hi>Abraham</hi> ſayd to the proude rich man in hell: <hi>Sonne,</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>remember that thou in thy life time haddeſt thy pleaſure, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Lazarus received paynes: but now he is comforted and thou art puniſhed.</hi> Arguing a matter of Iuſtice to giue tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and paynes after death to them that haue giuen themſelues to paſtime and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this life: which alſo S. <hi>Iames</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 5.</note> in a manner confirmeth in his <hi>5.</hi> Chapter. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that <hi>Moſes</hi> hauing hereof right conſideration, did not only put off his ſhooes from his feete, the clogges that might haue hindred him from comming to the Lord and from doing his duetie:<note place="margin">Exod 3.</note> but alſo he choſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction with the people of God in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> before the pleaſures of ſinne in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> for a ſeaſon. The Lord in his mercie perſwade vs with <hi>Iaphet</hi> to departe from the ſocietie and pleaſures of <hi>Cham,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dwell in the tabernacles of bleſſed <hi>Shem,</hi> that we may not ſerue the deuill among the
<pb facs="tcp:17358:50"/> manie of this world in theſe vaine and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pleaſures, which confounded <hi>Sodom,</hi> and with them <hi>Lots</hi> wife.</p>
               <p>Further, wee note in this woman a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of Gods prouidence mixt with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carefulneſſe;<note place="margin">5 Diſtruſt of Gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; worldly carefulnes.</note> inconueniences which alway followe infidelitie. O woman, thou diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting one thing, takeſt care for many things. Doeſt thou thinke, that the great omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God is not thereby ritch and liberall, mightie and moſt willing to prouide for his children? Could not he haue giuen thee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without <hi>Sodom?</hi> And wilt thou di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt him and care for thy ſelfe without him? Wilt thou looke backe to the things left behinde thee in <hi>Sodome?</hi> The Hebrew text hath it thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is, <hi>his wife looked back behind her.</hi> Which the Greeke tranſlation yeeldeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. that is: <hi>She loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked backe, or had reſpect to the things behind her, or on that which ſhe had left in Sodom.</hi> She thought that God would not haue ſo well prouided for her, elſwhere, as ſhe was prouided for in <hi>Sodom:</hi> therfore ſhe had a carefull deſire of the things left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde her, and a mind to prouide for her ſelf.
<pb facs="tcp:17358:51"/> Thus the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting God, wiſhed for the fleſh and fare of <hi>Egypt</hi> agayne. Oh that ſhe had remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the goodneſſe of God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and her owne huſband <hi>Lot.</hi> She neuer ſawe the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeede to begge. Behold, he feedeth the yong Rauens that crye vnto him: and will he not feed his own children? Do bodily fathers offer vnto their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſtones but bread, and not Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions but fiſhes: and ſhall not our heauenly father giue good things to ſuch as aſke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him? Shall the birdes feede their Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and the beaſtes their young, and will not he feede his children? O woman, what meaneſt thou? Would to God this maladie had not alſo infected vs; then would we not by ſuch indirect meanes as wee vſe, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to prouide for our backe and our bellie: then would wee not ſo murmur agaynſt God, as we do with mindes neuer content. But ſome do decipher themſelues hereby to be not true ſonnes, but baſtards. For if we aſſure our ſelues to bee his children, and be our father, then alſo do wee aſſure our ſelues of his prouiſion for vs, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs, as the apple of his eye, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:17358:51"/> one hayre of our head to periſh, much leſſe our life. He fed <hi>Eliah</hi> by the miniſterie of Rauens: he ſent meate to <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions denne: he fed an hundred Prophets by the hand of <hi>Obadiah</hi> in Caues: he gaue water to <hi>Sampſon</hi> from the Iaw bone of an Aſſe, and honie from the dead carcaſſe of a Lion: the widowes had their oyle and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer encreaſed in the famine. He gaue Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na from heauen, water from the Rocke, and Quayles from the ayre vnto the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> In <hi>Samaria</hi> there is plentie of flower on a ſodayne: and our Sauiour Chriſt feedeth ſometime <hi>4000.</hi> ſometime <hi>500.</hi> perſons with fine loaues and two fiſhes, and yet more is taken vp in fragments, then was layd downe in the whole. Why then ſhould we murmur? Why ſhould we exceſſiuely care for the morrowe and vexe our mindes? Let vs rather applie our vocations accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of his word with the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie and lawfull meanes, and affixe our mindes on him and truſt in his mercie, knowing that man liueth not by bread only, but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> cryed for fleſh, they haue it and dye thereof for their
<pb facs="tcp:17358:52"/> murmuring diſtruſt. And ſo <hi>Lots</hi> wife di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting God, ſhe murmureth in mind, ſhe bendeth back, as though her owne care had been better than Gods grace for her ſaftie: but ſhe hath a reward. Remember her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt and worldly carefulnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6 Fooliſh pitie.</note>Another fault we find in this faithles wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (as cords of vanitie do euer linck to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to pull men from God,) and that is fooliſh pitie, which is alſo too common among vs. She was moued for her friends and old acquaintance, whoſe companie and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhe loued, which ſhe ſhould rather haue hated: and ſhe thought it a pitifull thing, that ſinners ſhould be puniſhed.<note place="margin">Pſa. 101.3</note> 
                  <hi>I hate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> to the Lord) <hi>that hate thee; and am grieved with them that riſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.4.</note> being perſuaded that he only ſhould dwell in the Lords tabernacle, and reſt vpon his holy hill, in whoſe eyes a vile perſon is contemned. Therefore he ſaith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine:<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.5.</note> 
                  <hi>I have hated the companie of the evill, a froward heart ſhall depart from me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 101.7</note> 
                  <hi>I will knowe none evill perſon:</hi> for thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>There ſhall no deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſon dwell in my houſe.</hi> Let Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates take heed of fooliſh pitie. Remember
<pb facs="tcp:17358:52"/> how King <hi>Saul</hi> for pitying <hi>Agag</hi> the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lakite,</hi> was reproued and plagued: that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab,</hi> for letting go of <hi>Benhadad</hi> King of <hi>Siria,</hi> was reprehended &amp; endangered. On the other ſide: Remember what <hi>Iehu</hi> did to <hi>Iezabel</hi> and the wicked houſe of <hi>Achab,</hi> without compaſſion, and that he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by the Lord for doing this thing, his ſonnes ſhould ſurely ſit on the throane after him to the third and fourth generation. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo, what a good report zealous <hi>Phinehas</hi> obtained, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his ſword he flewe <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> and ceaſſed the plague, which was accounted vnto him for righteouſnes throughout all generations. And it is for euery man to be zealous in the Lords cauſe with Chriſt (who was deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the zeale of his fathers houſe) not to giue ayme to ſinne, nor ſuffer the honor of the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be prophaned: but to deſire with heart the conuerſion of ſinners, to withſtand their open abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to reproue ſinne, and by lawfull meanes to ſéeke the execution of iuſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne: euery maiſter in his houſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery father in his family, and euery true Chriſtian in his place, is to take heed that
<pb facs="tcp:17358:53"/> he withſtand ſinne in his ſeruants, in his children, in his brethren, though with repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, with due correction, and the lawfull execution of the end of iuſtice, as the caſe or cauſe ſhall require without fooliſh pitie. But how negligently this is obſerued, the verie ſtreetes of the Citie do teſtifie, when as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, children, and thoſe that ſhould knowe how to meaſure their words with diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be nothing fearefull to ſweate and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the holy name of God in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conferences: neither do they ſhame to commit ſinne openly as <hi>Sodom</hi> did, and there is found no iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> to reproue them: but there be found too many maiſters, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and others, that with <hi>Lots</hi> wife will rather giue ayme vnto their vngodlines, and be vnwilling in hart that any correction, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion or puniſhment at all ſhould be giuen them, <hi>Remember Lots wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another fault is found in this vnhappie woman, ſlouth and negligence<note place="margin">7 Slouth, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</note> in hir iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney foorth. There is none excuſe can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Lords commandement, neither the ſtammering toong of <hi>Moſes</hi> that could not ſpeake, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tendernes of <hi>Ieremy</hi> being but a child, nor the ſimplicitie of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:53"/> the leaſt among his brethren, nor the pouertie of <hi>Gedeon</hi> ſo meane, nor the baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of <hi>Ionas</hi> ſo fearefull, nor the former life of <hi>Saul</hi> a perſecutor, may iuſtly offer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes of delayes in their lawfull vocation. But ſéeme the thing neuer ſo hard, ſtrange, obſcure, vneaſie or impoſſible,<note place="margin">Note this.</note> if the Lord once bid vs to procéede, we may not bée ſlacke nor negligent, nor refuſe to obeye. And this is taught vs by many examples: <hi>Peter</hi> in priſon is commanded to riſe vp quickly, and ſo he did.<note place="margin">Acts. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Zacheus</hi> being called from the figge tree by our Sauiour, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downe quickly. The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did eate the Paſſouer haſtely as they were commanded, and <hi>Paul</hi> doth the worke of the Lord without negligence, as the Spirit moueth him. We muſt ſtrike whiles the iron is hoate, and ſeeke the Lord whiles he may be found, for the tyde carieth for no man. We muſt knock in time,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55. Eccles. 3.1.</note> and enter in before the gate be ſhut: for there is a time of mercie, and a time of wrath: of mercie, whiles <hi>Abraham</hi> praieth, and <hi>Lot</hi> is yet in <hi>Sodom:</hi> of wrath, when <hi>Abraham</hi> ceaſſeth to pray, and <hi>Lot</hi> is departed. Do not then ſay, when ye are called by the word of the
<pb facs="tcp:17358:54"/> Lord to come to him: I am but young, and too young to ſerue God yet: I will ſerue him when I am old: ſay not, I will firſt go and burie my father, I wil go &amp; bid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> farewell at home: neither make delayes or excuſes by buying Oxen, fyning farmes, marying wiues: but to day, if ye will heare the Lords voice, harden not your hearts: The Lord promiſeth not to ſtay for you till to morrow, though he promiſe that at what time ſoeuer ye repent, he will forgiue you. Therefore delay not, he only winneth the goale that runneth ſwiftly, he obtaineth the victorie that ſtriueth valiantly, he entreth into the gate, that waiteth carefully, and he is heard worthely, that craueth timely. Runne then, make haſte, the day is at hand, the time is vncertaine, the enemie is ſtrong, <hi>Sodom</hi> is ſinfull, the Angels be come to deſtroy the vngodly, the cale is taken, the Lord is not intreated, the nomber of the godly is ſmall, there is none to ſtop the Lords wrath, not one to ſtand vp in the gap for the Citie that can be heard, and the fire will not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, therefore it is more then time to flye hence. Heereat <hi>Lot</hi> with his two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do runne hence with his ſpeede, but
<pb facs="tcp:17358:54"/> his wife hath many heauie clogs, ſhe is ſlouthfull, negligent, full of delayes, and is ouertaken with deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this vngodly Woman being by the deuill, the world, and the fleſh,<note place="margin">8 Apoſtacie.</note> ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely hindered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good courſe, now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in the end maketh ſhipwrack of all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for ſhe doth apoſtate and turne backe from the Lord to <hi>Sodom.</hi> There be two kinds of returnes,<note place="margin">2. kinds of returne.</note> the one good &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, the other wicked and abhominable. It is a good thing to turne vnto the Lord, and to change our ſelues, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>by true Repentance,</hi> to amend &amp; become new creatures in Chriſt. This is that new birth which Chriſt ſheweth to <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Iohn. 3.</hi> and this bringeth mercie and forgiuenes in Chriſt, righteouſnes, holines, and eternall glorie. But it is a dangerous thing to turne back againe, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to the dog that reſumeth his vomit againe, and to the ſowe being waſhed, to her wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing againe in the mire. She went from <hi>Sodom,</hi> and ſéemed to procéede well for a time with her huſband: but ſhe ſhould alſo haue quite forgotten her owne people, and her fathers houſe: ſhe being in the féeld,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:55"/> ſhould not haue turned backe to that ſhe left in the Citie. Héere be two in one bed, the one receiued, the other forſaken. An hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite<note place="margin">An hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.</note> giueth a ſhew of that which is not: ſo did <hi>Lots</hi> wife: but now it is apparant what ſhe is, when with <hi>Demas</hi> ſhe leaueth <hi>Paul,</hi> and turneth back to <hi>Sodom</hi> ward. Nothing feigned is of continuance, nor an hypocrite can long conceale the malice of his mind, <hi>Quis enim relaverit ignem? <hi>Cayne</hi>
                  </hi> gaue a faire ſhew for a time, he ſacrificed as <hi>Abell</hi> did, though not with <hi>Abels</hi> heart. King <hi>Saul</hi> ſhewed many reſemblances of vertue, but wherevnto that grew, it appeared plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his diſobedience.<note place="margin">2. King.</note> King <hi>Ioas</hi> in the life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of <hi>Iehoida</hi> the Prieſt, by whome he was inſtructed, procéeded with commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but <hi>Iehoida</hi> being taken away, he plainely deciphereth himſelfe, by murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Prophet, and committing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes againſt God. <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſtale away the hearts of the people: <hi>Oh that I were King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>then would I do iuſtice?</hi> but his hypocriſie in the end appéered moſt publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Iezabel</hi> had her Prophets, and when <hi>Naboth</hi> ſhould be put to death, ſhe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded holines by proclaiming a faſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. but her
<pb facs="tcp:17358:55"/> wickednes is bewraied and puniſhed. So <hi>Herod</hi> pretended a deſire to go and worſhip Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he determined to murther him: and <hi>Iudas</hi> was for the poore in open ſhewe, becauſe he bare the bagge, and would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the poore. Thus the verie Deuil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being moſt execrable wicked, will yet tranſforme himſelfe into an Angell of light, till he hath brought foorth the lumpe of his lewdnes, to the diſhonor of God, and hurt of men:
<q>
                     <l>Et gandet ſe neſciri, &amp; ſua facta lateri:</l>
                     <l>Et nocuiſſe tamen, ſed non nocuiſſe videri.</l>
                  </q> And ſo ſecretly doth he wrap vp his deuiſes, that when he hurteth moſt, he will pretend greateſt honeſtie. And thus <hi>Lots</hi> wife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth her ſecret folly in the end, by her bending backe. She now fully declareth what ſhe is, by forſaking her vocation and backſliding.</p>
               <p>Learne heere by the way, that the worke of the Lord muſt not only be taken in hand, but alſo continued:<note place="margin">The work of the Lord muſt be continued</note> in token thereof, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hath his long coate, and the verie tayles of the beaſts were ſacrificed with their bodies, and he that is vnworthy, and continueth not in his calling accordingly, hath this cenſure
<pb facs="tcp:17358:56"/> layd on him by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Epiſcopatum cius accipiat alter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 2. Pſal. 109.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him be taken away, and another put in his place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It had bin good for thée, thou Wife of <hi>Lot,</hi> to haue called to mind thine Aunt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Abrahams</hi> Wife, who béeing faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, denied not, but moſt willingly conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to follow her huſband at the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, from <hi>Vr</hi> of the <hi>Caldees,</hi> with a long iourney and great danger, into an vnknowne and ſtrange land, to her great commendation, and how that God had eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie way prouided mercifully for her, but ſhe forgat all, being blinded with impietie: I pray God we be not forgetfull with <hi>Lots</hi> wife.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">There haue bin many good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>We haue heard of many good women ſithence then, that do teach vs continuance, and an obedient willingnes in our duties. What is ſaid of <hi>Rebekah?</hi> ſhe left her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, and accompanied <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant vnto <hi>Izhak</hi> her huſband with great chaſtitie: alſo <hi>Leah</hi> and <hi>Rahel</hi> the wiues of <hi>Iaakob</hi> came with him from their fathers houſe willingly: <hi>Naomi</hi> goeth with her huſband <hi>Elimelech</hi> into <hi>Moab,</hi> when foode wanted in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Rahab</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:17358:56"/> 
                  <hi>Ierico, Zipporah</hi> the wife of <hi>Moſes, Anna</hi> the wife of <hi>Tobias,</hi> and <hi>Sarra</hi> his ſonnes wife, <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of Chriſt, and many other good women, haue moſt worthely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their faith by chriſtian conſtancie: thus ought we to do: and ſo ſhould <hi>Lots</hi> wife haue done: for theſe women before mentioned, were righteous in their liues, and be in memorie with the Saincts: but this vnhappy woman by bending backe from her huſband, and ſo from God, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be vnrighteous and infamous among the reprobate for euer.</p>
               <p>Oh that we were frée from ſuch women! and all men from their infections: but it is to be feared, that too manie in theſe our dayes, euen now whiles the Goſpell is yet preached, and the Sonne of righteouſnes giueth vs light, do refuſe to follow their huſbands, and them that are willing to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, I will not ſay into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, but euen into the Church where the word of God is preached. If <hi>Lots</hi> wife was puniſhed then for that, alas what iudgements remaine for theſe? This I ſay, ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> héede of backſliding. Remember the iudgements of God on ſuch hypocrites
<pb facs="tcp:17358:57"/> and Apoſtates. <hi>Remember Lots wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>3. The puniſhment of Lots wife.</head>
                  <p>This wretched bodie eſcapeth not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her rewarde and puniſhment, and ſo much the ſorer is ſhe plagued, for that once ſhe began to followe, but afterward looked backe and forſooke him. It had been much better for her neuer to haue come forth from <hi>Sodom,</hi> then being come foorth agayne to returne. Of this turning about ſpeaketh the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes, Chap. 6.4.</hi> and <hi>Chap. 10.26.</hi> ſaying: <hi>It is impoſsible for ſuch to bee renewed by repentance: for there remayneth no more Sacrifice for ſinnes, but a fearefull expectation of the Iudgement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and violent fire which ſhall deuoure the adverſaries:</hi> This is a terror to them that conſider both the ſinne and the iudgement: but a bitter hell and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them that feele the ſame. Let the Magiſtrate, the Miniſter, the people, the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the countrie, and our whole land by the due conſideration hereof bee humbled in feare, and pray heartely to the Lord to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them from this outragious euill.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:57"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lots</hi> wife is plagued: but doth not her huſband herein helpe her?<note place="margin">The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not the wife in this plague.</note> Note here. The preheminence of the good man cannot ſerue the euill woman herein. Then take heede, waxe not bold on other mens vertues: truſt not to others oyle. <hi>Abſalom</hi> was <hi>Dauids</hi> ſonne, and <hi>Eſau</hi> firſt borne vnto <hi>Izhak:</hi> but what of that? They be both reiected: haue faith in God: haue faith in your ſelues: the iuſt man liueth by his owne faith, and not by anothers faith. Though <hi>Daniel, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> had been there, yet could not this vngodly woman eſcape, no, albeit <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> prayed for the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and among them for her: yet ſhe periſheth, becauſe ſhe remayned euill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lot</hi> periſheth not among the wicked: but <hi>Lots</hi> wife being wicked. And although his two daughters for his comfort in his great ſorowe are with him brought foorth from <hi>Sodom,</hi> yet may not they boaſt of their merites: but rather ſtand in awe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſinne no more. Neither can it profite any man, that his father, mother, wife, brother or ſiſter are godly and accepted with the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.</note> except that himſelfe do immitate and reſemble them truely in godlineſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:17358:58"/> 
                     <hi>Lots</hi> wife being wicked, eſcapeth not with the iuſt man, but periſheth.</p>
                  <p>But what plague ouertooke this vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie woman?<note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of her plague.</note> A plague of bodie, and torment of ſoule. But leauing her ſoule to the ſecrete iudgements of God among the ſinfull <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites,</hi> with whom ſhe periſhed: we finde it mentioned in the Scripture, <hi>Gen. 8.</hi> That ſhe was turned into a pillar of Salt, ſtanding as a monument to the poſterities. Inaſmuch as ſhe was a chaungeling, ſhe was chaunged: ſhe turned about and ſhe is turned. A ſodayne chaunge and ſtraunge Metamorphoſis, not faigned by the Poets, but wrought in deede by the power of God, teſtified by his holie Spirite, wrote in a booke by <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſeruant, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by our Lord Chriſt for our inſtruction.</p>
                  <p>The Poets faigne tranſformations of ſhapes, ſome into birdes: ſome into beaſtes, ſome into trées, ſome into ſtones: but a more true Metamorphoſis we haue teſtified in the Propheſie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> of <hi>Nabucadnezzar,</hi> the Monarke of the earth, who became as a beaſt of a brutiſh and ſauage minde. Yet here a more maruailous tranſformation: A righteous mans wife is turned into a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="tcp:17358:58"/> of Salt. Her minde was not only mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous in her life: but her bodie alſo, a note of inconſtancie and iniquitie in her death.</p>
                  <p>I knowe that ſome of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> haue giuen this Interpretation:<note place="margin">Pet. Mar. in <hi>Gen.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Et fuit cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus, vel ſtatua ſalis.</hi> And there was an heape or pillar of Salt: not of <hi>Lots</hi> wife, but of the earth, which ſhe ſawe behind h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> when ſhe looked backe to <hi>Sodom.</hi> She did ſee, ſay they, the earth or the land, and it was an heape of Salt, by reaſon of the burning: but this Interpretation is ouerthrowne by theſe reaſons. Firſt, the daughters of <hi>Lot</hi> would not haue vrged ſeede of their father,<note place="margin">Sap. 10.7.</note> had their mother been then liuing. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the Wiſe man ſayth of her: for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the vnfaithfull Soule, there ſtandeth a pillar of Salt. Thirdly, <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> witneſſeth, that he ſawe ſuch a pillar of Salt. Fourthly, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is of the opinion, that ſuch a thing was done in deed: that is, <hi>in Salem verſam eſſe vxorem Loth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Lots wife was chaunged into a pillar of Salte.</hi>
                     </hi> Laſtly, Chriſt himſelfe noteth in her a ſtraunge puniſhment, when talking of the <hi>Iewes</hi> Apoſtaſie and latter deſtruction, he ſayth: <hi>Remember Lots wife.</hi> So we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:17358:59"/> that this is to be vnderſtood of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man her ſelfe: and therefore as wee receiue it, doth <hi>Munſter</hi> tranſlate, <hi>Et facta eſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua Salis: <hi>She was made a Salt ſtone, or pillar.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She is turned into a pillar or ſtone:<note place="margin">A ſtone.</note> to note, the hardneſſe of her heart, which the true propheſie of the Angels and the words of her huſband could not mollifie. A ſtone, to note her coldneſſe in the true Religion, wherein zeale is required, and heat of Gods grace. A ſtone, to note the nature of ſuch, as like ſtones, will rather reſiſt the drops of rayne, than receiue moyſture, as the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and ſtubborne hearts accuſtome to do. A ſtone, to note her barrayne breaſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull faith. A ſtone, not of the corner, but caſt aſide and ſet alone, though not in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico,</hi> yet not in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but betweene them both: not in <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor yet in <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> but in the wilderneſſe, where many haue periſhed for want of faithfull continuance. She halteth betweene both: And therefore is ſhe loathed of the Lord and abandoned of good men. She ſtandeth as a pillar, not for any goodneſſe in her ſelfe, but to note her vngodlineſſe, fooliſhneſſe, and plague. She
<pb facs="tcp:17358:59"/> is famed, but yet with diffame, as <hi>Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus,</hi> who to get him a name ſet the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Diana</hi> on fire. She was reſpited a while for her huſbands ſake: but now is ſhe plagued for her owne ſinnes. <hi>Sodom</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing helpeth her, for it cannot helpe it ſelf. Her glorie is turned into ſhame by her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, which ſhe gayned before, by her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming foorth. She deſperatly falleth head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into miſfortunes, and might (if God would) haue incurred the plagues of <hi>Kain</hi> for his murther: of <hi>Saule,</hi> for his diſobedience: of <hi>Nabal,</hi> for his fooliſhneſſe: of <hi>Iezebel,</hi> for her ſorceries: of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> for her treacheries: of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> for his blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: but yet ſhe hath another kinde of plague: for ſhe is turned into a pillar of Salt.</p>
                  <p>Salt ſignifieth, ſometimes diſcretion,<note place="margin">Why ſhe is turned into Salt. Col. 4.</note> the word of God, Doctrine. And Salt is good if it want not ſauour. And the Apoſtle would that our Doctrine bee ſo ſeaſoned. <hi>Plinie</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>31.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> vſeth a Metaphor taken from the vſe of Salt. In all meates it is vſed in ſteede of a Sawce to eſchew greedineſſe and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyte. Neither can a man well liue without Salt. So neceſſarie an element is it. Such
<pb facs="tcp:17358:60"/> are the ornaments of mans life. And it is commaunded in the lawe, that euery Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice ſhall be ſeaſoned with Salt: to note, that no Sacrifice can pleaſe God,<note place="margin">Leuit. 2.</note> but that which is done with diſcretion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is charged, <hi>Ne auferes Sal faederis dei tui de Sacrificio tuo: <hi>Thou ſhalt alwaies vſe Salt in euery gift, which thou ſhalt offer vnto mee, by reaſon of the Couenant which I haue made with thee.</hi>
                     </hi> And for the doctrine of truth, the Apoſtles be called <hi>Sal terrae, <hi>The Salt of the earth:</hi>
                     </hi> for as Salt is bitter to the taſte, and fretteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the corruptions of the fleſh, ſo is the truth vnto ſinfull man. Howbeit, this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable woman is by that nothing the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, inaſmuch as that which is now in her, ſerueth wholie to the vſe of other, and not of her ſelfe. She is like in this to the heart of a poyſoned man, which as ſome ſay, will not burne, but waxe hard in the fire, as a ſtone, and will become a ſoueraigne medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin for others againſt poiſon. She ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth therefore a piller of Salt for a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cument vnto others, which by her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample flying the like puniſhment, are the happier.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17358:60"/>
                  <p>Beſides that, ſhe is ſalt in another ſenſe, for ſalt doth not only note diſcretion, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, doctrine, and ſuch, but alſo it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth barraines: <hi>for euery place of the earth where ſalt is found</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plin. li. <hi>31.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note>) <hi>is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, and apt to no fruite.</hi> Therefore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi> (as we reade in the ninth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the booke of the <hi>Iudges</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note>) ſowed ſalt in <hi>Sichem.</hi> And ſo ſpeaketh <hi>Zephenaiah:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>As I liue,</hi> ſayth the Lord of hoaſtes, the God of <hi>Iſrael, ſurely Moab ſhall be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon, as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morah, euen the breeding of Nettles and Salt pits, and a perpetuall deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And ſuch a place doth <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 34.13</note> deſcribe in his <hi>34.</hi> Chapter, ſpeaking of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Sinagogue (a worthie fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure whereof appeareth in this woman) he that readeth it, let him vnderſtand it. And thus haue we ſéene the puniſhment and plague of <hi>Lots</hi> vnfaithfull, and ſo vnequall yokefellow: <hi>Oh remember this ye that forget God: O kiſſe the Sonne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. Pſal. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>leaſt he be angrie, and ſo ye periſh from the right way, if his wrath be kindled againſt you euen but a little: Oh put away diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out of your hearts,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and remoue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
<pb facs="tcp:17358:61"/> from your bodyes in ſeaſon, for childhood and youth, is but vanitie.</hi> Let vs conſider to what ende we haue our mindes and memories giuen vs: let vs with thankefulnes remember God and his mercies towards vs: let vs thinke of our ſinnes, and amend our liues with faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: let vs knowe the time of our viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with watchfulnes: let vs beware of thoſe horrible ſinnes noted in <hi>Lots</hi> wife, and eſchue the danger of her puniſhment with godlie carefulnes. Let the Magiſtrate continue his calling without wearines: the Miniſter go too and hold on the Plough without loathſomnes, the people procéede in their calling without ſluggiſhnes, the Citie to fight in faith without faintnes, the Countrey to be religious without maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and the whole land to ſerue the Lord without fearefulnes. Let this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>Iapheth,</hi> to dwell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Tabernacles of <hi>Shem:</hi> let this moue <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to eſchue the polluted bed of <hi>Potiphar:</hi> euery chaſte <hi>Suſanna</hi> to denie the deſire of the vngodlie Elders: euery <hi>Shiphrah,</hi> and <hi>Puah</hi> (as they did in <hi>Aegypt</hi>) to feare the Lord, and not men. Let this ſtirre vp <hi>Mordecai,</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:17358:61"/> prouide for the ſafetie of his people: Quéene <hi>Heſther,</hi> to pray for her ſelfe and her people, and euery faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> to forſake old <hi>Adam,</hi> and the affections of man. Let vs all with that kinglie Prophet <hi>David,</hi> deſire to be rather doorekeepers in Gods houſe, then to dwell in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of the vngodly. Let vs with <hi>Moſes</hi> rather chooſe affliction with the people of God in the Wildernes, than the pleaſures of Sinne in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Let vs deſire rather <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> than <hi>Ierico,</hi> and <hi>Canaan,</hi> before <hi>Babylon.</hi> Let vs flye from <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> with iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe with <hi>Lots</hi> wife.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> Let vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede from vertue to vertue, and be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the ſame: Let vs ſet God euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our faces, as our Sauiour Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs: and let vs with <hi>S. Paul</hi> fight a good fight: keepe on the good courſe: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end conſtantlie without fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: expecting faithfully that eternall Crowne of glorie, which all ſuch as by the bloud of Chriſt the immaculate Lamb haue bin Victors, ſhall be crowned with in his euerlaſting Kingdome. This grace and bleſſednes the Almightie graunt vnto
<pb facs="tcp:17358:62"/> vs, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake: to whome, with the holie Ghoſt, three perſons, and one moſt mightie and eternall God, be aſcribed all honor, might, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and dominion, now, and for euermore.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17358:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
